<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Divine consolations for mourners in Sion being an extract of certain choyce epistles of dying martyrs to each other and to their fellow prisioners for the cause of Christ, in the times of cruell and fiery persecution, wherein is much variety of suitable matter of meditation for all such who are burthened under the pressure of their sins and sorrows in these evil times.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1664</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 207 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 66 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B08933</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1719</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC W41420</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">61296959</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 61296959</idno>
            <idno type="VID">180526</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B08933)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 180526)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2832:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Divine consolations for mourners in Sion being an extract of certain choyce epistles of dying martyrs to each other and to their fellow prisioners for the cause of Christ, in the times of cruell and fiery persecution, wherein is much variety of suitable matter of meditation for all such who are burthened under the pressure of their sins and sorrows in these evil times.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 78 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Cambridge :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place publication suggested by Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Trinity College (Dublin, Ireland). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Consolation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:180526:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>DIVINE</hi> CONSOLATIONS FOR MOURNERS in SION: Being an EXTRACT of certain Choyce EPISTLES OF DYING MARTYRS To each other, and to their Fellow Priſoners for the CAUSE OF CHRIST, <hi>In the Times of Cruell and Fiery Perſecution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein is much Variety of ſuitable matter of Meditation for all ſuch who are burthened under the Preſſure of their Sins and Sorrows in theſe EVIL TIMES.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Matth. 5.4.</hi>
                  </bibl> Bleſſed are they that mourn: for they ſhall be comforted.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſal. 126.5.</hi>
                  </bibl> They that ſow in tears, ſhall reap in joy.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Ver. 6.</hi>
                  </bibl> He that goeth forth and weepeth, bearing precious ſeed, ſhall doubtleſs come again with rejoycing, bringing his ſheaves with him.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1664.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:180526:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:180526:2"/>
            <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Good Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong all the ſweet and precious fruits and graces of the Spirit of God held forth unto us in the Holy Scriptures, how much are thoſe of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Love</hi> commended unto us, as the principal and leading Graces unto all other the ſweet fruits of the Spirit wrought in the hearts of the Elect of God?</p>
            <p>To inſtance two or three places speaking to this purpoſe: The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> in his Catalogue of Saints,<note place="margin">Hebr. 11.</note> how highly doth he advance the actings of Faith in their hearts and lives, beginning with <hi>Abel,</hi> that bleſſed Servant of the Lord, and Proto-Martyr of the World, whom our bleſſed Lord and Saviour honoureth with the ſame honour, placing his Name in the Front of that bleſſed Company (by the Name of <hi>Righteous Abel</hi>) who had laid down their lives in the Cauſe,<note place="margin">Matth. 23.35.</note> and for the Truths of God? And for the grace of <hi>Love,</hi> in that of <hi>1 Cor. 8. the beginning;</hi> whatever Inſtructions the Apoſtle had given them before, he doth as it were recall himſelf, and let them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that all would prove as nothing, unleſs it proceed from Love or Charity. And further we are taught, that although the grace of Faith be firſt in laying hold of the bleſſed object, even our Lord Jeſus, who came into the World to ſave ſinners, yet this alſo of Love is by the gracious working of the ſame good Spirit of God begotten in the Soul, even at the ſame inſtant of time with that of Faith, and from
<pb facs="tcp:180526:3"/> their firſt appearing come forth as bleſſed Twins never to part again, the ſame bleſſed Spirit carrying on the work of Grace in the Soul, untill perfected in Glory. To this purpoſe <hi>Gal. 5.6.</hi> it's ſaid to be <hi>Faith which worketh by Love.</hi> Alſo to mention no more, <hi>1 Tim. 1.14. The grace of our Lord was exceeding abundant, with Faith and Love which is in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> A Reverend Meſſenger of Chriſt lately compared them to the two Arms that clasped Chriſt about, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that of the Spouſe, <hi>Cant. 3.5. It was but a little that I paſſed from them, but I found him whom my Soul loveth; I held him, and would not let him go.</hi> Never do theſe precious gifts of the Holy Ghoſt ſo affect the hearts of the people of God, as when the Saints are drawn forth to cauſe this Light to ſhine forth in their lives and act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, which uſually appears in them moſt clearly in times of greateſt Sufferings. How much are we of theſe times bound unto our gracious God, for the innumerable helps the Lord hath this way granted us, especially from the unwearied Labours of that man of God, of bleſſed memory, Mr. <hi>Iohn Fox,</hi> out of whoſe rich Volumes this little Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe following is taken, being a particular brief ſtory of him whoſe Soul as much longed for the Crown of Martyrdome, (although he paſſed through the Fire to it) as any we reade of from the time of the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Martyrs. And notwithſtanding the Lord of his Infinite wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, denyed him that which he ſo much thirſted for, reſerving him (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in Priſon) yet to be an Inſtrument who from his great experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences might Adminiſter ſweet Conſolations unto others (the ſweet Saints and Martyrs of Jeſus) as indeed he did, to the refreſhing of many a good Soul, as by the ſeveral excellently Spiritual Epiſtles of his doth manifeſtly appear; and by which it may undoubtedly be gathered, that himſelf was to be accounted among the bleſſed number of thoſe that in his Generation <hi>loved the Lord Jeſus Chriſt in Sincerity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To thoſe who have taſted how good the Lord is, theſe following Epiſtles may through mercy prove unto them as that ſpeaking of <hi>David</hi> did to <hi>Ionathan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 18.1.</note> who no ſooner heard him, but <hi>his Soul was knit with the Soul of David, and he loved him as his own Soul.</hi> To this very end is this ſmal thing drawn out of the aforeſaid Volume, that the ſorrowful Souls of ſuch as are affected with Gods threatnings in this hour of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and temptation, may finde ſome refreſhing and ſupport; to which
<pb facs="tcp:180526:3"/> very end alſo they were firſt written by the Au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hor.</p>
            <p>God is greatly threatning on every ſide, even us who have ſate in peace whileſt our Breth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en lay bleeding; yea, were filled with plen y, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>leſt they were ſtripped of their comforts, and even brought near to deſolation: ſurely we hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> n t improved our precious opportunities, but with <hi>Ieſurun,</hi> being <hi>waxed fat, have lifted up the heel;</hi> and now may juſtly fear, that our day of viſitation is haſtening, wherein we are like to drink of the Cup of Gods diſpleaſure, of which the Nations have begun before us. Is not the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rd now crying aloud, as ſometimes to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> Oh <hi>New-England!</hi> Oh <hi>Boſton!</hi> When will thou be made clean? when will it once be? when ſhall thy Pride and Propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Licentiouſneſs, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs, with ſo much cleaving to Self-intereſt ceaſe to lodge within thee? Bleſſed be the Lord, who hath affected the hearts of thy Rulers, ſo as to call for ſeeking God by Faſting and Prayer, being the way and meanes of Gods appointment for the obtaining mercy in the day of thy diſtreſs. The Lord hear thee in the day of thy ſeeking,<note place="margin">Joel 2.13, 14.</note> and teach thee to <hi>Rent thy heart and not thy garments, and turn unto the Lord, who knoweth if he will return and repent, and leave a bleſſing behind him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh that God would give his People an heart to hearken to his voice, and to turn unto him by unfeigned Repentance, for ſurely they that yet ſee it not, are like ſhortly to ſee,<note place="margin">Amos 5.13.14, 15.</note> that <hi>this time is a time for the Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to keep ſilence, for it is an evil time,</hi> as the Prophet ſaith; therefore let us <hi>ſeek good and not evil, and ſo the Lord God of Hoſts ſhall be with us: Let us hate evil and love good, and eſtabliſh Judgement in the Gate, it may be that the Lord God of Hoſts will be gracious to the remnant of</hi> Joſeph.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:180526:4"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:180526:4"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:180526:5"/>
            <head>A Table of the ſeveral Epiſtles and Letters contained in this Book.</head>
            <list>
               <item>THe effect of <hi>John Careles</hi> his Examination before Dr. Martin, <hi>Folio</hi> 1</item>
               <item>A Letter of Mr. <hi>Philpot</hi> to <hi>John Careles,</hi> profitable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o be read of all them which mourn in Repentance for their ſins, 6</item>
               <item>A Letter of <hi>John Careles,</hi> Anſwering to the loving Epiſtle or Letter ſent to him before by Mr. <hi>Philpot,</hi> 10</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Bradfords</hi> Letter to <hi>Careles,</hi> 14</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Careles</hi> his Letter to Mr. <hi>Bradford,</hi> 15
<list>
                     <item>His Letter to his Wife, 18</item>
                     <item>His Letter to ſeveral faithful Brethren in Newgate, Condemned for the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Gods Everlaſting Truth, 21</item>
                     <item>His Letter to Mr. <hi>Green,</hi> Mr. <hi>Whittel,</hi> and certain other Priſoners in Newgate, Condemned and ready to be burnt for the Teſtimony of the Lord Jeſus, 26</item>
                     <item>His Letter to <hi>W. Tyms</hi> Priſoner in Newgate, 29</item>
                     <item>His Letter to his dear Siſter Mrs. <hi>Cotton,</hi> 33</item>
                     <item>His Letter to his dear Brother <hi>T. V.</hi> 34</item>
                     <item>His Letter to his dear and faithful Brother <hi>Auguſtine Bernher,</hi> 38</item>
                     <item>His Letter to his dear Brother <hi>Henry Aalington,</hi> Priſoner in the Lollard<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Tower, 42</item>
                     <item>His Letter to his dear and faithful Brother <hi>T V.</hi> 47</item>
                     <item>His Letter of Thanks to a faithful Friend of his, by whom he had received much Comfort in his inward Troubles, 51</item>
                     <item>His Letter to a certain godly faithful Siſter, by the Name of <hi>E. K.</hi> 52</item>
                     <item>His Letter to Mrs <hi>Agnes Glaſcock,</hi> 55</item>
                     <item>His brief Admonition to Mrs <hi>Agnes Glaſcock,</hi> written in a book of hers when ſhe came to the Priſon to viſit him, 57</item>
                     <item>His Letter to Mrs. <hi>A. G.</hi> to comfort her in her Repentance after ſhe had been at Maſs; fruitful for all them to reade, which are faln, and are to be raiſed up again, 58</item>
                     <item>His Letter to <hi>A. B.</hi> a frithful Miniſter of the Lord, containing certain fruitful Precepts of Matrimony, 61</item>
                     <item>His Letter to Elizabeth, Wife of the ſaid <hi>A. B.</hi> containing likewiſe certain godly Precepts of Matrimony pertaining to her duty, 64</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>A Letter of Mr <hi>John Bradfords,</hi> which he wrote to a faithful Woman in her heavineſs and trouble: moſt comfortable for all thoſe to read that are afflicted and broken hearted for their ſins, 68</item>
               <item>A worthy Anſwer of a conſtant Martyr called <hi>Guy de Brez,</hi> Anno Dom. 1566. 75</item>
               <item>The ſame Martyr in a Letter to his Wife, acquaints her with Gods Gracious dealing with him in all his Aſſaults, <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="examination">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:180526:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE</hi> EFFECT OF <hi>JOHN CARELES</hi> EXAMINATION before <hi>Doctor Martin</hi> briefly declared.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Effect of John Careles ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination.</note> Doctor Martin <hi>calling</hi> John Careles <hi>to him in his Chamber, demanded what was his Name. To whom when the other had anſwered, that his name was</hi> John Careles, <hi>then began</hi> Doct. Martin <hi>to deſcant at his pleaſure upon that name, ſaying, That it would appear by his conditions by that time he had done with him, that he would be a true Careleſs man indeed. And ſo after other by-talk there ſpent about much needleſs matter, then he asked him where he was born?</hi>
            </p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Careles.</speaker>
               <p>Forſooth, ſaith he, at Coventry.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Martin.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>At Coventry? what ſo far man? How cam'ſt thou hither? who ſent thee to the Kings Bench to Priſon?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Careles.</speaker>
               <p>I was brought thither by a Writ, I trow;<note place="margin">How John Care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les was brouht to the Kings Bench</note> what he was I cannot tell. I think <hi>Mr. Marſhall</hi> can tell you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Marſh.</speaker>
               <p>In good faith I cannot tell what the matter is: but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed my Lord Chief Juſtice ſent him from the Barr.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Well</hi> Careles, <hi>I would wiſh thou ſhould'ſt play the wiſe mans part. Thou art an handſom man; and it is pitty but that thou ſhouldſt do well, and ſave that which God hath bought.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Careles.</speaker>
               <p>I thank your good Maſterſhip moſt heartily: And I put you out of doubt that I am moſt ſure and certain of my ſalvation by Jeſus Chriſt; ſo that my ſoul is ſafe already, whatſoever pains my body ſuffer here for a little time.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yea Marry, you ſay truth: for thou art ſo Predeſtinate to life, that thou canſt not periſh, in whatſoever Opinion thou doeſt dye.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Careles.</speaker>
               <p>That GOD hath Predeſtinate me to Eternal life in Jeſus Chriſt, I am moſt certain;<note place="margin">John Careles examined upon Predeſtination.</note> and even ſo am I ſure that his Holy Spirit (wherewith I am ſealed will ſo preſerve me from all Hereſies and evill Opinions, that I ſhall dy in none at all.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb facs="tcp:180526:6"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:180526:6"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <sp>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:180526:7"/>
               <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Go to, let me hear your Faith in Predeſtination: for that ſhall be written alſo.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Carel.</speaker>
               <p>Your Maſterſhip ſhall pardon me herein. For you ſaid your ſelf ere-while, that you had no Commiſſion to examine my Conſcience. I will trouble my ſelf with anſwering no moe matters then I needs muſt, untill I come before them that ſhall have more authority further to examine me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Martin</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion.</note>
                  <hi>I tell thee then I have Commiſſion; yea, and Commandement from the Council to examine thee: for they delivered me thy Articles.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Carel.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, I think indeed that your Maſterſhip is appointed to examine me of my Articles which you have there in writing, and I have told you the truth. I do confeſs them to be mine own fact &amp; deed: but you do now examine me of Predeſtination, whereof my Articles ſpeaketh nothing at all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I tell thee yet again, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat I muſt alſo examine thee of ſuch things as be in controverſie between thee and thy fellows in the Kings Bench, whereof Predeſtination is a part, as thy fellow</hi> N. <hi>hath confeſſed, and thy ſelf doſt not deny it.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Carel.</speaker>
               <p>I do not deny it. But he that firſt told you that matter, might have found himſelf much better occupied.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Why Dr. <hi>Martin</hi> would not exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine him of the Sacrament.</note>
                  <hi>Why? what if he had not told me? thinkeſt thou I would not have known it? yes, or elſe thou ſhouldſt have withſtood my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion. For I tell thee truth, I may now examine thee of the bleſſed Sacrament, or any other thing that I liſt, but that I would ſhew thee favour, and not be too haſty with thee at the firſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Marſh.</speaker>
               <p>Yea indeed <hi>Careles,</hi> Maſter Doctor hath Commiſſion to examine you, or any other of your fellow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yea marry have I, I tell the truth of it.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Careles.</speaker>
               <p>Then let your Scribe ſet his pen to the paper, and you ſhall have it roundly even as the truth is. I believe that Almighty GOD, our moſt dear loving Father, of his great mercy and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs did Elect in Chriſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tuſh, What need all that long circumſtance? write, I believe that God Elected; and make no more ado.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Careles.</speaker>
               <p>No not ſo Mr. Doctor: it is an high Myſtery, and ought reverently to be ſpoken of. And if my words may not be
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:180526:7"/> written as I do utter them, I will not ſpeak at all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Go to, go to, wri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e what he will, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> is more buſineſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> then needeth.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Careles.</speaker>
               <p>I believe that Alm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ghty God our moſt dear loving Father,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Careles</hi> Opinio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of Gods Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note> of his great mercy and infinite goodneſs (through Ieſus Chriſt) did elect and appoint in him before the foundation of the Earth was laid, a Church or Congregation, which he doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually guide and govern by his Grace and holy Spirit, ſo that not one of them ſhall ever finally periſh. When this was written, Mr. Doctor took it in his hand and read it, ſaying,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why? who will deny this?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">D. <hi>Martin</hi> avow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Careles</hi> judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Gods Election.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Careles.</speaker>
               <p>If your Maſterſhip do allow it, and other learned men when they ſhall ſee it, I have my hearts deſire.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And do you hold none otherwiſe then is there written?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Careles.</speaker>
               <p>No verily, nor never did.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Write that he ſaith otherwiſe he holdeth not. So that was written. It was told me alſo that thou doſt affirm that Chriſt did not dye effectually for all men.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Careles.</speaker>
               <p>Whatſoever hath been told you, it is not much material unto me. Let the tellers of ſuch tales come before my f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce, and I truſt to make them anſwer. For indeed I do b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lieve that Chriſt did effectually dye for all thoſe that do effectually repent and believe, and for none other. So that was written alſo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now ſir what is</hi> Trewes <hi>faith of Predeſtination? he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth that all men be Predeſtinate, and that none ſhall be Damned: doth he not?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Careles.</speaker>
               <p>No forſooth, that he doth not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How then?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Careles</speaker>
               <p>Truely I think he doth believe as your Maſterſhip and the reſt of the Clergy do believe of Predeſtination,<note place="margin">A wrong faith of Predeſtination, believing to be elected in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of Good works.</note> that we be Elected in reſpect of our good works, and ſo long elected as we do them and no longer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Write that he ſaith, his fellow</hi> Trew <hi>believeth of Predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation as the Papiſts do believe.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Careles.</speaker>
               <p>Ah Mr. Doctor, did I ſo term you? ſeeing that this my Confeſſion ſhall come before the Council, I pray you place my terms as reverently as I ſpake them.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb facs="tcp:180526:8"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:180526:8"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:180526:9"/>
               <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Well, well. Write that</hi> Trew <hi>is of the ſame Faith as the Catholicks be.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Careles.</speaker>
               <p>I did not ſo call you neither, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> wonder what you mean.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Marſh.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>You ſaid th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Clergy, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Careles?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Careles</speaker>
               <p>Yes forſooth did I So then it was written of the Clergy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now Sir What ſay you more?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Careles.</speaker>
               <p>Forſooth I have no further to ſay in this matter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Martin</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth favour to <hi>Careles.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Well,</hi> Careles, <hi>I pray thee prove thy ſelf a wiſe man, and do not caſt away thy ſelf wilfully.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Careles.</speaker>
               <p>Now the Lord he knoweth, good Mr. Doctor, I would full gladly live, ſo that I might do the ſame with a ſafe Conſcience. And your Maſterſhip ſhall right well perceive that I will be no wilful man, but in all things that I ſtand upon, I ſhall have a ſure ground.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now the Lord knoweth, good</hi> Careles, <hi>that I would gladly make ſome means to preſerve thy life; but thou ſpeakeſt ſo much of the Lord, the Lord: wilt thou be content to go with my Lord</hi> Fitzwater <hi>into</hi> Ireland? <hi>methinks thou art a goodly tall fellow to do the Queen ſervice there. How ſayeſt thou?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Careles.</speaker>
               <p>Verily Mr. Doctor, whether I be in <hi>Ireland, France,</hi> or <hi>Spain,</hi> or any place elſe, I am ready to do her Grace the beſt ſervice I can, with Body, Goods and Life, ſo long as it doth laſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>That is honeſtly ſaid. I promiſe thee every man will not ſay ſo. How ſay you Mr. Marſhall, this man is meet for all manner of Service. Indeed thou art worthy</hi> Careles <hi>to have the more favour.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Careles.</speaker>
               <p>Indeed Sir I hope to be meet and ready unto all things that pertaineth unto a true Chriſtian Subject to do. And if her Grace, or her Officers under her, do require me to any thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary unto Chriſts Religion, I am ready alſo to do my ſervice in Smithfield for not obſerving it, as my bedfellow and other Brethren have done: praiſed be God for them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>By my troth thou art a pleaſant fellow as ever I talked with of all the Proteſtants, except it were</hi> Tomſon. <hi>I am ſorry that I muſt depart with thee ſo ſoon: but I have ſuch buſineſs now, that I can tarry with thee no longer. Well, yet thou canſt not deny, but you are at
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:180526:9"/> jarre amongſt your ſelves in the Kings B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h, and it is ſo throughout all your Congregation, for you will not be a Church.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Careles.</speaker>
               <p>No Mr. Doctor that is no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſo.<note place="margin">More variety in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Popes Church then is amongſt the Proteſtants.</note> There is a thouſand times more variety in Opinions among your Doctors, which you call of the Catholick Chu ch, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ea and that in the Sacrament, for the which there is ſo much bloodſhed now adayes: I mean of your latter Doctors, and new Writers; as for the old, they agree wholly with us.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>No</hi> Careles, <hi>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t is not ſo: there thou art deceived.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Careles.</speaker>
               <p>Verily it is ſo, Mr. Doctor. I am not deceived therein any thing at all, as it hath been, and is evidently proved by ſuch as God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath indued with great Learning. Then he turned to the Marſhal and whiſpered with him a while.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Turning unto me again, ſaid, Farewel</hi> Careles,<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Martin</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his leave gently of <hi>Careles.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>for I can tarry no longer with thee now my buſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſs is ſuck.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Careles.</speaker>
               <p>God be with you good Mr. Doctor. The Lord give your Maſterſhip health of Body and Soul.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Martin.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>God have mercy, good</hi> Careles; <hi>and God keep thee from all Errours, and give thee grace to do as well as I would w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſh my ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Careles.</speaker>
               <p>I thank your good Maſterſhip. I pray God I may do always that is acceptable in his ſight. Whereunto they all ſaid <hi>Amen.</hi> And ſo I departed with a glad heart: God onely have the whole praiſe. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It appeareth by Examination of the foreſaid <hi>John Careles,</hi> that he endured Priſoner the ſpace of two whole years having wife and Children. In the which his captivity firſt being in Coventry Goal, he was there in ſuch credit with his Keeper, that upon his word he was let out to play in the Pageant about the City with other his Companions. And that done, keeping touch with his Keeper, he returned again into Priſon at his hour appointed.</p>
               <p>And after that being brought up to <hi>London,</hi> he was endued with ſuch patience and conſtant fortitude,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>John Careles</hi> dv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Priſon and w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s buried in the fields.</note> that he longed for nothing more earneſtly, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n to come to that promotion to dye in the fire for the profeſſion of his Faith: and yet it ſo pleaſed the Lord to prevent him with death, that he came not to it, but dyed in the
<pb facs="tcp:180526:10"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:180526:10"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:180526:11"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:180526:11"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:180526:12"/> Priſon, and after was buried in the fields in a dunghill.</p>
               <p>In the mean time while he was in Priſon in the Kings Bench, it chanced he was in great heavineſs, and perturbation of minde and Conſcience: whereupon he wrote to <hi>M. Philpot</hi> being then in the Colehouſe. Upon occaſion hereof, <hi>M. Philpot</hi> ſent an Epiſtle Conſolatory unto him, as followeth.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A Letter of Mr. <hi>Philpot</hi> to <hi>John Careles,</hi> profitable to be read of all them which mourn in Repentance for their Sins.</head>
            <p>THe God of all comfort, and the Father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, ſend unto thee my dear Brother <hi>Careles,</hi> the inward conſolation of his holy Spirit, in all the malicious aſſaults and troublous temptations of our common Adverſary the Devil. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That GOD giveth you ſo contrite an heart for your ſins, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but rejoyce to behold the lively mark of the children of God, whoſe property is to think <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore lowly and vilely of themſelves then of any other, and oftentimes do ſet their ſins before them, that they might the more be ſtirred to bring forth the fruits of Repentance, and learn to mourn in this world, that in another they might be glad and rejoyce. Such a broken Heart is a pleaſant Sacrifice unto God: Oh that I had the like contrite heart. God mollifie my ſtony heart, which lamenteth not in ſuch wiſe my former deteſtable iniquities. Praiſed be God that he hath given you this ſorrowfull heart in respect of Righteouſneſs; and I pray you let me be partaker of theſe godly ſorrows for ſin, which be the teſtimony of the preſence of the holy Ghoſt. Did not the ſword of ſorrow pierce the heart of the Elect and bleſſed Mother of our Lord? Did not <hi>Peter</hi> weep bitterly for his ſins, which was ſo beloved of Chriſt? Did not <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> waſh the feet of our Saviour with her tears, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived therewithall remiſſion of her ſevenfold ſins?</p>
            <p>Be of good comfort therefore, <hi>Mine own dear heart,</hi> in this thy ſorrow, for it is the Earneſt-peny of Eternall Conſolation. In thy ſorrow laugh, for the Spirit of God is with thee. <hi>Bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſed be they</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>that mourn,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 15.</note> 
               <hi>for they ſhall be comforted. They went forth and wept,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 126.</note> ſaith the Prophet; <hi>ſuch ſhall come again,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:180526:12"/> having their gripes full of gladneſs.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 51. Luke 7. Sorrow in a Chriſtian man ought to be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate.</note> And al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hough a ſorrowfull heart in conſideration of his ſin, be an acceptable Sacrifice before God, whereby we are ſtirred up to more thankefulneſs unto God, knowing that <hi>much is fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ven us, that we might love the more:</hi> yet the man of God muſt keep a meaſure in the ſame, leſt he be ſwallowed up by too much ſorrow.<note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 4.</note> S <hi>Paul</hi> would not the <hi>Theſſalonians to be ſorry as other men which have no hope.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 7.</note> Such a ſorrow is not commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, but worketh damnation, and is farre from the children of God, who are continually ſorrowfull in God, when they look upon their own unworthineſs, with hope of forgiveneſs. For God to this end by his Spirit ſetteth the ſins of his Elect ſtill before them,<note place="margin">Rom. 3.</note> that where they perceive <hi>Sin to abound,</hi> there they might be aſſured that <hi>Grace ſhall ſuperabound:</hi> and bringeth them down into Hell, that he might lift them up with greater joy into Heaven. Wherefore, <hi>mine own Bowels in Chriſt,</hi> as long as you are not void altogether of hope, be not diſmayed through your penſive heart for your ſins, how huge ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they have been, for God is able to forgive more then you are able to ſin; yea, and he will forgive him which with hope is ſorry for his ſins.</p>
            <p>But know, Brother, that as oft as we do go about, by the help of Gods Spirit, to do that is good,<note place="margin">Satans practice to bring the godly repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of a ſinner to deſperation.</note> the evil spirit Satan layeth hard wait to turn the good unto evil, and goeth about to mix the deteſtable D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rnell of Deſperation, with the godly Sorrow of a pure Penitent Heart. You be not ignorant of his malicious ſubtilty, and how that continually he aſſaulteth that good which the grace of God planteth. I ſee the battel betwixt you and him, but the victory is yours, yea and that daily: For you have laid hold upon the Anchor of Salvation, which is <hi>hope in Chriſt,</hi> he which will not ſuffer you to be made aſhamed.</p>
            <p>Be not diſcomforted that you have this Conflict: but be glad that God hath given you the ſame to try your Faith, and that you might appear daily worthy of the Kingdome of God, for the which you ſtrive. God beholdeth your ſtriving Faith againſt Satan, and is pleaſed with your mighty reſiſtance. The Spirit which is in you, is mightier then all the Adverſaries power. Tempt he may, and lying await at your heels, give you a fall unawares: but overcome he ſhall not; yea he cannot, for you are ſealed up already with a lively Faith to be
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:180526:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:180526:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:180526:14"/> the childe of God for ever: and whom God hath once ſealed for his own, him he never utterly forſaketh.<note place="margin">Gods children fall. The Devils chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren lye ſtill.</note> The juſt falleth ſeven times, but he riſeth again. It is mans frailty to fall, but it is the property of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils childe to ly ſtill.</p>
            <p>This ſtrife againſt ſin is ſufficient teſtimony that you are the childe of God,<note place="margin">Luke 11.</note> for if you were not, you ſhould feel no ſuch malice as he now troubleth you withall. When this ſtrong <hi>Goliah</hi> hath the hold, all things be in peace which he poſſeſſeth; and becauſe he hath you not, he will not ſuffer you unaſſaulted. But ſtand f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt, and hold out the Buckler of Faith,<note place="margin">Strife againſt ſin is a token of Gods childe.</note> and with the Sword of Gods Promiſes ſmite him on the ſcalp, that he may receive a deadly wound, and never be able to ſtand againſt you any more.<note place="margin">James 4.</note> S. James telleth you that he is but a coward, ſaying, <hi>Reſiſt the Devil, and he will fly away.</hi> It is the will of God that he ſhould thus long tempt you, and not go away as yet, or elſe he had done with you long ere this. He knoweth already that he ſhall receive the foyle at your hands, and increaſe the Crown of your Glory: for <hi>he that overcometh ſhall be crowned.</hi> Therefore g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ory in your temptation, ſince they ſhall turn to your felicity. Be not afraid of your continuall aſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ults, which be occaſions of your daily victory. The Word of G d ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eth for ever. <hi>In what hour ſoever a ſinner repenteth him of his ſins they be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 33.</note> 
               <hi>Who can lay any thing to the charge of Gods Elect?</hi> Do you not perceive the manifeſt tokens of your Election? Firſt your voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Gospel, and after your vocation, the manifeſt gifts of the Spirit of God given unto you above many other of your condition, with godlineſs which believeth and yieldeth to the authority of the Scriptures, and is zealous for the ſame? Seeing you are Gods own dearling, who can hurt you? Be not of a deject minde for theſe temptations, neither make your unfeigned friends to be more ſorrowfull for you, then need doth require.</p>
            <p>Since God hath willed you at your Baptiſm in Chriſt to be <hi>Careles,</hi> why do you make your ſelf Carefull? <hi>Caſt all your care on him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Set the Lord before your eyes alwayes, for he is on your right ſide that you ſhall not be moved.</hi>
               <note place="margin">True Chriſtians how they ought to be c releſs in their carefull eſtate.</note> Behold the goodneſs of God toward me. I am careleſs, being faſt cloſed in a Pair of Stocks, which pinch me for very ſtraitneſs; and will you be carefull? I will not have that unſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly addition to your Name. Be as your Name pretendeth, for doubtleſs
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:180526:14"/> you have none other cauſe but ſo to be. Pray, I beſeech you, that I may be ſtill careleſs in my carefull eſtate, as you have cauſe to be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs in your eaſier condition. Be thank<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>full, and put away all care, and then I ſhall be joyfull in my ſtrait preſent care. Commend me to all our Brethren, and deſire them to pray for me that I may overcome my tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations; for the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vil rageth againſt me. I am put in the Stocks in a place alone, becauſe I would not anſwer to ſuch Articles as they would charge me withall in a corner at the Biſhops appointment, and becauſe I did not come to Maſs when the Biſhop ſent for me. I w ll lye all the dayes of my life in the Stocks (by Gods grace) rather then I will conſent to the wicked generation. Praiſe God and be joyfull that it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him to make us worthy to ſuffer ſomewhat for his Names ſake. The Devil muſt rage for ten dayes. Commend me to Mr. <hi>F.</hi> and thank him for his Law-books; but Law, neither Equity will take any place among theſe blood thirſty. I would for your ſake their unjuſt deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing were noted unto the Parliament-houſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, if it might avail. God ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten theſe evil dayes. I have anſwered the Biſhop meetly plain already, and I ſaid to him, If he will call me in open Judgemen, I will anſwer him as plainly as he will require: otherwiſe I have refuſed, becauſe I fear me they will condemn me in hugger-mugger. The peace of God be with you my dear Brother. I can write no more for lack of light, and that I have written I cannot reade my ſelf, and God knoweth s is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten farre uneaſily. I pray God you may pick out ſome underſtanding of my minde towards you. Written in a Colehouſe of da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>kneſs out of a Pair of painfull Stocks, by</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine own in Chriſt, <hi>John Philpot.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:180526:15"/>
            <head>A Letter of <hi>John Careles</hi> anſwering to the loving Epiſtle or Letter ſent to him before by Mr. <hi>Philpot.</hi>
            </head>
            <q>
               <p>A faithfull friend is a ſtrong defence, whoſo findeth ſuch an one, findeth a treaſure.</p>
               <p>A faithfull friend hath no peer, the weight of gold and ſilver is not to be compared to the goodneſs of his Faith.</p>
               <p>A faithfull friend is a Medicine of life, and they that fear the Lord ſhall finde him. <bibl>
                     <hi>Eccleſiaſt. 6.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A lett<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r of <hi>John Careles</hi> to Mr. <hi>Philpot.</hi>
               </note>THe Father of Mercy, and God of all Conſolation, comfort you with his Eternal Spirit (my moſt dear and faithful loving Friend good Mr. <hi>Philpot</hi>) as you have comforted me by the mighty operation of the ſame: The everlaſting God be praiſed therefore for ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ah my dear heart, and moſt loving Brother, if I ſhould do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe day and night, ſo long as the dayes of Heaven do endure, but kneel on my knees and reade Pſalms, I can never be able to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der unto God condign thanks for his mercy, fatherly kindneſs, and moſt lov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng compaſſion extended unto me moſt vile, ſinful, wicked and unworthy wretch. Oh that the Lord would open my mouth, and give me a thankful heart, that from the bottom of the ſame might flow his continual praiſe. Oh that my ſinful fleſh (which is the cauſe of my ſorrow) were clean ſeparated from me, that I might ſing Pſalms of Thankſgiving unto the Lords Name for ever: that with good <hi>Samuels</hi> Mother, I might continually record this noble Verſe following, the which by good experience I have found moſt true, praiſed be my good God therefore.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 2. <hi>John Careles</hi> raiſed up by the Lord out of great heavineſs.</note>
               <hi>The Lord</hi> (ſaith that good woman) <hi>killeth, and maketh alive; he bringeth down to hell, and fetcheth up again.</hi> Praiſed be that Lord for ever, yea, and praiſed be his Name, for that he hath given me true experience and lively feeling of the ſame. Bleſſed be the Lord God, whoſe mercy endureth for ever, which hath not dealt with me ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my deep deſerts, nor deſtroyed me in his diſpleaſure when I had juſtly deſerved it. Oh what reward ſhall I give again unto
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:180526:15"/> the Lord for all the great benefits that he hath done for my Soul! I will gladly receive the Cup of Salvation at his hand, and will worſhip his Name with Prayer and with Praiſe.</p>
            <p>Ah my dear heart, yea moſt dear unto me in the Lord think not this ſudden change in me to be ſome fickle Phantaſie of my fooliſh head (as indeed ſome other would ſurely ſuſpect it to be) for doubtleſs it is the marvellous doing of the Lord, moſt merciful un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me his unworthy Creature God for his great mercies ſake give me grace to be more thankful unto him then I heretofore have been, and keep me that I never fall forth of his favour again.</p>
            <p>And now my dear Brother, and moſt bleſſed M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſenger of the Lord whoſe beautiful feet have brought much glad tidings unto my Soul, what ſhall I do or ſay unto you, in the leaſt part to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence the fatherly affection and godly care that you continually keep for me? Oh that God would give me the Spirit of fervent Prayer, that I might yet that way ſupply ſome little part of my duty toward you. Ah my true loving Friend, how ſoon did you lay aſide all other buſineſs, to make a ſweet Plaiſter for my wounded Conſcience, yea and that out of a painful Pair of Stocks, which place muſt needs be uneaſie to write in. But God hath brought you into a ſtrait place, that you might ſet my Soul at liberty. Out of your pinching and painful Seat, you have plentifully poured up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me your precious Nard, the ſweet ſavour whereof hath greatly refreſhed my tyred Soul. The Lord likewiſe refreſh you both Body and Soul, by pouring the oyle of his gracious Spirit into your ſweet heart.</p>
            <p>Ah good <hi>Jeremy,</hi> hath <hi>Paſhur</hi> put thee in the Stocks? why,<note place="margin">Jer. 20.</note> now thou haſt the right reward of a Prophet. Thy glory never began to appear till now. I doubt not but ſhortly,<note place="margin">Jer. 26.</note> in ſtead of <hi>Ahikam</hi> the the Son of <hi>Shaphan, Jeſus</hi> the Son of the living God will come, and deliver thee forth of the hands of all thine Enemies, and will alſo make good againſt them and their Antichriſtian Synagogue, all the words that thou haſt ſpoken in his Name. The Lord hath made thee this day a ſtrong defenced Tower, an iron Pillar,<note place="margin">Jer. 1.</note> and a brazen Wall againſt the whole Rabble of Antichriſt: and though they fight againſt thee never ſo fiercely, yet ſhall they not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:180526:16"/> thee, for the Lord himſelf is with thee to help and deliver thee;<note place="margin">Jer. 15.</note> and he will rid thee out of the hands of the wicked, and will deliver thee out of the hands of the Tyrants. And in that you are not buſie in <hi>caſting Pearls before Swine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 7.</note> nor in <hi>giving the holy things unto Dogs,</hi> you are much to be commended in my ſimple judgement.<note place="margin">The circumſpect behaviour of Mr. <hi>Philpot.</hi>
               </note> And ſure I am, that your circumſpect and modeſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour hitherto hath been as much to Gods glory, and to the ſhame and confuſion of your enemies, as any man's doings that are gone before you.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>John Careles</hi> his advice to him.</note>Wherefore mine advice and moſt earneſt deſire is, with all other of your loving Friends, that you ſtill keep that order with thoſe Blood-thirſty Bite-ſheeps, <hi>Biſhops</hi> I ſhould ſay, that you have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun. For though in concluſion they will ſurely have your blood, yet ſhall they come by it with ſhame enough, and to their perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual infamy whiles the world doth endure. They would indeed condemn you in hugger-mugger, to darken Gods glory, if it might be: but Satans thoughts are not unknown to you, and the depth of his ſubtilty is by you well foreſeen. Therefore let them do what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever God ſhall ſuffer them to do; for I know all things ſhall tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n to your beſt. Though you lie in the dark, ſlurried with the Biſhops black Cole-duſt, yet ſhall you be ſhortly reſtored unto the heavenly Light, and made <hi>as white as ſnow in Salmon, and as the wings of a Dove,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 68.</note> 
               <hi>tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is covered with ſilver wings, and her feathers like gold.</hi> You know the Veſſel, before it be made bright, is ſoiled with Oyle and other things, that it may ſcoure the better.</p>
            <p>Oh happy be you, that you be now in the Scouring-houſe, for ſhortly you ſhall be ſet up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the Cel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>al ſhelf as bright as Angels. Therefore, <hi>my dear hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> I will now according to your loving re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, caſt away all care, and rejoyce with you, and praiſe God for you, and pray for you day and night,: yea, I will now, with Gods grace, ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g Pſalms of Praiſe and Thankſgiving with you: for now my Soul is turned to her old reſt again, and hath taken a ſweet nap in Chriſts lap. I have caſt my care upon the Lord, which careth for me, and will be careles, according to my Name, in that reſpect which you would have me. I will leave out my unſeemly addition as long as I live; for it can take no place where true faith and hope
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:180526:16"/> is reſident.<note place="margin">Gods gracious work through M <hi>Philpots</hi> Letter.</note> So ſoon as I had read your moſt godly and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable Letter, my ſorrows vaniſhed away as ſmoke in the wind, my Spirit revived, and comfort came again, whereby I am ſure the Spirit of God was Author of it.</p>
            <p>Oh good Mr. <hi>Philpot,</hi> which art a principal Pot indeed, filled with moſt precious Liquor, as it appeareth by the plenteous pouring forth of the ſame. Oh Pot moſt happy, of the high Potter or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to honour, which doſt contain ſuch heavenly treaſure in the Earthen veſſel! Oh Pot thrice happy, in whom Chriſt hath wrought a great Miracle, altering thy nature, and turning water into wine, and that of the beſt, whereout the Maſter of the Feaſt hath filled my cup ſo full,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John Careles</hi> drunken with joy of the ſpirit.</note> that I am become drunken in the joy of the Spirit thorow the ſame. When Martyrdome ſhall break thee (O veſſel of honour) I know the fragrant ſavour of thy precious Nard will much rejoyce the heavy hearts of Chriſts true Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, although the <hi>Judaſſes</hi> will grudge and murmure at the ſame; yea, and burſt out into words of ſlander, ſaying, <hi>It is but loſt and waſte.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Be not offended, <hi>dear heart,</hi> at my Metaphorical ſpeech; for I am diſpoſed to be merry,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 6.</note> and with <hi>David</hi> to <hi>dance before the Ark of the Lord:</hi> and though you play upon a pair of Organs not very comely or eaſie to the fleſh, yet the ſweet ſound that came from the ſame, cauſeth me thus to do. O that I were with you in body, as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently as I am in ſpirit, that I might ſing all care away in Chriſt; for now the time of comfort is come. I hope to be with you ſhortly, if all things happen aright:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Careles</hi> accuſed to the Council by certain backe friends in <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventry.</hi>
               </note> for my old friends of <hi>Coventry</hi> have put the Council in remembrance of me, not ſix dayes ago, ſaying, <hi>That I am more worthy to be burned then any that was burned yet.</hi> Gods bleſſing on their hearts for their good report. God make me worthy of that dignity, and haſten the time, that I may ſet forth his Glory.</p>
            <p>Pray for me, <hi>dear heart,</hi> I beſeech you, and will all your company to do the ſame, and I will pray God for you all ſo long as I live. And now farewell in Chriſt, thou bl ſſed of Gods own mouth,<note place="margin">Note how com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable the Lord worketh in his priſoned Saints.</note> I will for a time take my leave, but not my laſt farewel. Bleſſed be the time that ever I came into the Kings Bench, to be joyned in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:180526:17"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:180526:17"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:180526:18"/> love and fellowſhip with ſuch dear Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ldren of the Lord. My good Brother <hi>Bradford</hi> ſhall not be dead whiles you be alive: for verily the ſpirit of him doth reſt on you in moſt ample wiſe. Your Letters of comfort unto me in each point do agree, as though the one were a copy of the other. He hath <hi>planted in me,</hi> and <hi>you do water,</hi> the <hi>Lord give good increaſe.</hi> My dear Brethren and fellow-priſoners here, have them humbly and heartily commended unto you, and your company, mourning for your miſery, but yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing for your plenteous Conſolation and comfort in Chriſt. We are all chearful and merry under our Croſs, and do lack no ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries, Praiſed be God for his Providence and great mercy towards us for evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>Mr. <hi>Bradfords</hi> Letter to <hi>Careles.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>ALmighty God our dear Father, through and for the Merits of his dearly beloved Son Jeſus Chriſt, be mercifull unto us, pardon us our offences, and under the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ngs of his Mercy protect us from all evil, from henceforth and for ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Dear Brother <hi>Careles,</hi> I heartily pray you to pray to God for me, for the pardon of my manifold ſins, and moſt grievous offences, which need none other demonſtration unto you then this, namely, That I have behaved my ſelf ſo negligently in anſwering your godly triple Letters, which are three Witneſſes againſt me. God lay not them, nor none other thing to my charge to Condemnation, though to Correction: <hi>Not my will,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Practice of the Keyes of the Goſpel.</note> 
               <hi>but his will be done.</hi> Concerning your requeſt of Abſolution <hi>(my deareſt Brother)</hi> what ſhall I ſay, but even as truth is, That the Lord of all Mercy, and Father of all Comfort, through the Merits and Mediation of his dear Son, thy onely Lord and Saviour, hath clearly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted and pardoned all thy offences whatſoever they be, that ever hitherto thou haſt committed againſt his Majeſty: and therefore he hath given to thee, as to his Childe (dear Brother <hi>John Careles</hi>) in token that thy ſins are pardoned; He (I ſay) hath given unto thee a penitent and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving heart; that is, a heart which deſireth to repent and believe: For ſuch an one is taken of him (he accepting the will for the deed) for a penitent and believing heart indeed.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:180526:18"/>
            <p>Wherefore <hi>(my good Brother)</hi> be merry, glad, and of good chear, for the Lord hath taken away thy ſins; thou ſhalt not dye. Go thy wayes, the Lord hath put away thy ſins. The Eaſt is not ſo farre from the Weſt, as the Lord now hath put thy ſins from thee. Look how the Heavens be in compariſon of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Earth, ſo farre hath his Mercy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed toward thee his dear Childe, <hi>John Careles,</hi> through Christ the Beloved. Say therefore with <hi>David, Praiſe the Lord, O my Soul, and all that is within me praiſe his holy Name:</hi> for he hath forgiven thee all thy ſins, as truely he hath. And hereof I deſire to be a Witneſs. God make me worthy to hear from you the like true Meſſage for my ſelf. Mine own dearly Beloved, you have great cauſe to thank God moſt heartily, that hath given you ſuch Repentance and Faith: The Lord increaſe the ſame in you, and me a moſt miſerable wretch, whoſe heart is harder then the Adamant ſtone, or elſe I could not thus long have ſtayed from writing unto you. If I live, and may, I purpoſe and promiſe you to make amends. Pray for me, my moſt dear Brother, I heartily beſeech you, and forgive me my long ſilence. God our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be with us for ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in the Lord, <hi>John Bradford.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>
               <hi>John Careles</hi> his Letter to Mr. <hi>Bradford.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe Peace of God in Jeſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">A ſweet Letter of <hi>John Careles</hi> to Mr. <hi>Bradford,</hi> a little before his Martyrdome</note> the Eternal Comfort of his ſweet Spirit, which hath ſurely ſealed you unto Eternal Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, be with you, and ſtrengthen you in your joyful journey to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Celeſtial <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> (my dear Friend, and moſt faithful Brother Mr. <hi>Bradford</hi>) to the ſetting forth of Gods glory, and to your eternal joy in Chriſt. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ever ſince that good Mr. <hi>Philpot</hi> ſhewed me your laſt Letter <hi>(my dear heart in the Lord)</hi> I have continued in great heavineſs and perplexity;<note place="margin">He mourneth for the loſs and l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ck of Mr. <hi>Bradfor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> in the Church.</note> not for any hurt or diſcommodity that I can perceive coming towards you, unto whom doubtleſs Death is made life and great felicity: but for the great loſs that Gods Church here in <hi>England</hi> ſhall ſuſtain, by the taking away of ſo godly, worthy, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:180526:19"/> neceſſary an inſtrument, as the Lord hath made you to be. Oh that my life, and a thouſand ſuch wretched lives moe, might go for yours! Oh why doth God ſuffer me, and ſuch other Catterpillers to live, that can do nothing but conſume the Alms of the Church, and take away you ſo worthy a Workman and Labourer in the Lords Vineyard? But woe be to our ſins and great unthanfulneſs, which is the greateſt cauſe of the taking away of ſuch worthy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of God, as ſhould ſet forth his Glory, and inſtruct his People. If we had been thankful unto God for the good Miniſters of his Word, we had not been ſo ſoon deprived both of it and them. The Lord forgive our great ingratitude and ſins, and give us true Repentance and Faith, and hold his hand of Mercy over us for his dear Son Chriſts ſake. Take not away all thy t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue Preachers forth of this Realm (O Lord) but leave us a Seed, leſt <hi>Engl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd</hi> be made like unto <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> when thy true <hi>Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> be gone.</p>
            <p>But what go I about to mingle your mirth with my mourning, and your juſt joy with my deſerved ſorrow? If I loved you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, as I have pretended, I ſhould ſurely rejoyce with you moſt heartily, and praiſe God on your b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>half from the very bottom of my heart:<note place="margin">He rejoyceth for the honour of Mr. <hi>Bradfords</hi> Martyrdome.</note> I ſhould praiſe God day and night for your excellent Election in and through his great Mercy and ſhould give him moſt humble thanks for your Vocation by his Goſpel, and your true Knowledge in the ſame: I ſhould earneſtly praiſe him for your ſweet juſtification, whereof you are moſt certain by Gods G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ace and Spirit; and ſhould inſtantly pray unto him for your Glorifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which ſhall ſhortly enſue: I ſhould rejoyce and be glad to ſee you dignified by the Crown of Martyrdome and to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to that honour, to teſtifie his Truth, and to Seal it with your Blood: I ſhould highly extoll the Lord, who hath given you a glorious v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctory over all your enemies, viſible and inv ſi le, and hath given you Grace and Strength to finiſh the Tower that you have begun to build. Finally, if I loved you, I ſhould moſt hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily rejoice and be glad to ſee <hi>you delivered from this body of ſin,</hi> and vile perſon of the Fleſh, and brought into <hi>that heavenly Tabernacle,</hi> where you ſhall be ſafely kept, and never offend him more.</p>
            <p>This and much more ſhould I do, if I had a good heart towards
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:180526:19"/> God, or you his dear childe. But (alas) I am an hypocrite, and do ſeek nothing but mine own commodity. I would have Gods everlaſting Providence give place to my peeviſh will and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, although it were to the hindrance of his glory, and your ſweet commodity. God forgive me my horrible ingratitude, ſins, and offences againſt him; and good Brother, do you forgive me my great negligence and unthankfulneſs towards you, and hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth I promiſe you I will put my will to Gods will, and pray that the ſame may be fulfilled in you, ſo long as you be on this earth: and when you are taken hence, I will moſt heartily praiſe the Lord for you, ſo long as I have my being in this world. Ah my dear heart, now I muſt take my leave of you, and as I think,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John Careles</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his leave of M. <hi>Bradford</hi>
               </note> my <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltimum Vale</hi> in this life, but in the life to come I am right well aſſured we ſhall merrily meet together, and that ſhortly, I truſt. And in taking of my leave of you <hi>(my dear heart in the Lord)</hi> I ſhall deſire you faithfully to remember all the ſweet meſſages that the Lord our good God, and moſt dear loving Father hath ſent you by me his moſt unworthy Servant, which as they are moſt true, ſo ſhall they be moſt truly accompliſhed upon you eternally: and for the more aſſurance and certificate thereof to your godly Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, he hath commanded me to repeat the ſame unto you again in his own Name and Word.</p>
            <p>Therefore now give ear, and faithful credence. Hearken,<note place="margin">Teſtimony of Gods Spirit.</note> O ye Heavens, and thou earth give ear, and bear me witneſs at the great Day, that I do here faithfully and truely the Lords m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge unto his dear Servant,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John Careles</hi> doth Gods meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage to M. <hi>Brad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford.</hi>
               </note> his ſingularly beloved and el<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ct Childe <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>n Brad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford. John Bradford</hi> thou man ſo ſpecially beloved of God, I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce and teſtifie unto thee in the Word and Name of the Lord Jehovah, that all thy ſins whatſoever they be, be they never ſo many, ſo grievous, or ſo great, be fully and freely p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>doned, releaſed and forgiven thee, by the mercy of God in Jeſus Chriſt thine onely Lord and ſweet Saviour, in whom thou doſt undoubtedly believe.<note place="margin">Power and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of the keyes of the Goſpel.</note> Chriſt hath cleanſed thee with his Blood, and clothed thee with his Righteouſneſs, and hath made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hee in the ſight of God his Father, without ſpot or wrinckle: ſo that when the fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e doth his appointed office, thou ſhalt be received (as a ſweet burnt Sacrifice) into
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:180526:20"/> Heaven, where thou ſhalt joyfully remain in Gods preſence for ever, as the true inheriter of his everlaſting Kingdome, unto the which thou waſt undoubtedly predeſtinate and ordained by the Lords in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible purpoſe and decree, before the foundation of the World was laid. And that is moſt true that I have ſaid, I call the whole Trinity, the Almighty and Eternal Majeſty of God the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt to my Record at this preſent: whom I humbly beſeech to confirm and ſtabliſh in thee the true and lively feeling of the ſame. <hi>Amen. Selah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now with a merry heart and a joyfull ſpirit, ſomething mixed with lawful tears, I take my farewel of you, mine own dear Brother in the Lord: who ſend us ſhortly a merry meeting in his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, that we may both ſing praiſes together unto him with his holy Angels and bleſſed Spirits for ever and ever. Farewel thou bleſſed of the Lord, farewel in Chriſt: depart unto thy reſt in the Lord; and pray for me for Gods ſake.</p>
            <p>As I had made an end of this ſimple Letter, I heard ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort both of good Mr. <hi>Philpots</hi> Servant and yours, but (alas) I do ſcarcely believe them. Well, I will hope in God, and pray all night that God would ſend me ſome comfort to morrow; and if the Lord give you ſparing to morrow, let me hear four words of comfort from you, for Gods ſake. The Bleſſing of God be with you now and for ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours for ever in the Lord Jeſus,</hi> John Careles living in Hope againſt Hope.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>
               <hi>John Careles</hi> his Letter to his Wife.</head>
            <p>AS by the great mercy of God, at the time of his good will and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence appointed, <hi>(my dearly beloved Wife)</hi> you and I were joyned together in the holy and Chriſtian ſtate of godly Matrimony, as well to our great joy and comfort in Chriſt, as alſo to the increaſe of his bleſſed Church and faithfull Congregation, by having lawfull Children in and by the ſame, with the which God of his mercy hath bleſſed us,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:180526:20"/> praiſed be his Name therefore: Even ſo now by his mercifull will and Divine Ordinance, the time is come (ſo farre as I can perceive) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he will, for his glory, and our eternall comfort, diſſolve the ſame, and ſeparate us aſunder again for a time. Wherefore I thought it good, yea and my bounden duty, by this ſimple Letter to provoke, ſtir, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh you to behave your ſelf in all your doings, ſayings and thoughts, moſt thankefully unto our good God for the ſame. And therefore <hi>(my dear Wife)</hi> as you have heartily rejoyced in the Lord, and oftentimes given God thanks for his goodneſs, in bringing us together in his holy Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance: Even ſo now I deſire you, when this time of our ſeparation ſhall come, to rejoyce with me in the Lord, and to give him moſt hearty thanks, that he hath (to his glory, and our endleſs commodity) ſeparated us again for a little time, and hath mercifully taken me unto himſelf forth of this miſerable world, into his Celeſtiall Kingdome;<note place="margin">Here is a true mark of a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Chriſtian, forſaking wife &amp; children for Chriſts ſake.</note> believing and hoping alſo aſſuredly, that God of his goodneſs, for his Son Chriſts ſake, will ſhortly bring you and your dear children thither to me, that we may moſt joyfully together ſing Praiſes unto his glorious Name for ever. And yet once again I deſire you for the love of God, and as ever you loved me, to rejoyce with me, and to give God continuall thanks for doing his moſt mercifull will upon me.</p>
            <p>I hear ſay, that you do oftentimes uſe to repeat this godly ſaying, <hi>The Lords will be fulfilled.</hi>
               <note place="margin">True obedience of a faithful wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</note> Doubtleſs it rejoyceth my poor heart to hear that report of you; and for the Lords ſake uſe that godly prayer continually, and teach your Children and Family to ſay the ſame day and night: and not onely ſay it with your tongues, but alſo with your heart and minde, and joyfully to ſubmit your will to Gods will in very deed; knowing and believing aſſuredly, that nothing ſhall come to you or any of yours, otherwiſe then it ſhall be his Almighty and Fatherly good will and pleaſure, and for your eternall comfort and commodity. Which thing to be moſt true and certain, Chriſt teſtifieth in his holy Goſpel, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Are not two little Sparrows ſold for a farthing?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 10.</note> 
               <hi>and yet not one of them ſhall periſh without the will of your heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> And he concludeth, ſaying, <hi>Fear not ye therefore, for ye are better then many Sparrows.</hi> As though he ſhould have ſaid, If God have ſuch a respect and care for a poor Sparrow, which is not worth one farthing, that it ſhall not be taken in the Lime-twig, Net, or Pit-fall,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:180526:21"/> unsill it be his good will and pleaſure; you may be well aſſured, that not one of you (whom he ſo dearly loveth, that he hath given his onely dear Son for y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u) ſhall periſh, or depart forth of this miſerable life, without his Almighty good will and pleaſure.</p>
            <p>Therefore, dear Wife, put your truſt and confidence wholly and onely in him, and ever pray that his will be fulfilled, and not yours, except it be agreeing to his will: the which I pray God it may ever be. <hi>Amen.</hi> And as for worldly things take you no care,<note place="margin">Good counſel given to his wife</note> but be you well aſſured the Lord your dear God and Father will not ſee you nor yours lack, if you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in his love and childly fear, and keep a clear Conſcience from all kind of Idolatry, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uperſtition, and Wickedneſs, as my truſt is that you will do, although it be with the loſs and danger of this temporal life. And good <hi>Margaret, Fear not them that can but kill the body,</hi> (and yet can they not do that, untill God give them leave) <hi>but fear to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſpleaſe him that can kill both body and Soul, and caſt them into hell fire.</hi> Let not the remembrance of your Children keep you from God: The Lord himſelf will be a Father and a Mother,<note place="margin">Care of children to be caſt upon Lord.</note> better then ever you or I could have been unto them. He himſelf will do all things neceſſary for them, yea as much as rock the Cradle, if need be. He hath given his holy Angels charge over them, therefore commit them unto him. But if you may live with a clear Conſcience (for elſe I would not have you to live) and ſee the bringing up of your Children your ſelf, look that you nurture them in the fear of God, and keep them farre from Idolatry, Superſtition,<note place="margin">The mothers duty in bringing up her children.</note> and all other kinde of Wickedneſs: and for Gods ſake help them to ſome Learning, if it be poſſible, that they may increaſe in virtue and god<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y knowledge, which ſhall be a better Dowry to marry them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, then any worldly ſubſtance: and when they be come to age, provide them ſuch Husbands as fear God, and love his holy Word. I charge you take heed that you match them with no Papiſts: and if you live and marry again your ſelf, (which thing I would wiſh you to do, if need require, or elſe not) good Wife take heed how you beſtow your ſelf, that you and my poor Children be not compelled to wickedneſs. But if you ſh ll be able well to live Gods true Widow, I would counſel you ſo to live ſtill, for the more quietneſs of your ſelf and your poor Children. Take heed, <hi>Margaret,</hi> and play the wiſe womans part: you have warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by other, if you will take an example. And thus I commit you and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:180526:21"/> my ſweet Children unto Gods moſt mercifull defence. The Bleſſing of God be with you, and God ſend us a merry meeting together in Heaven. Farewell in Chriſt: farewell mine own dear hearts all. <hi>Pray, pray.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>To my moſt dear and f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ithful Brethren in <hi>Newgate,</hi> Condemned to dye for the Teſtimony of Gods everlaſting Truth.</head>
            <p>THe everlaſting p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ace of G d in Jeſus Chriſt, the continual joy, ſtrength and comfort of his moſt p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re, holy, and mighty Spirit, with the encreaſe of Faith, and l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vely feeling of his Eternal Mercy be with you, my moſt dear and faithful lov ng B other <hi>Tyms,</hi> and with all the reſt of my dear hearts in the Lord, your faithful Fellow-ſouldiers, and moſt conſtant Companions in Bonds, yea, of men condemned moſt cruelly for the ſincere Teſtimony of Gods everlaſting Truth, to the full finiſhing of that good work, which he hath ſo graciouſly begun in you all, that the ſame may be to his glory, the commodity of his poor afflicted Church, and to your everlaſting comfort in him. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ah my moſt ſweet and loving B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ethren, and deareſt hearts in the Lord, what ſhall I ſay, or how ſhall I write unto you in the leaſt point or part, to utter the great joy that my poor heart hath recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in God, through the moſt godly example of your Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an Conſtancy, and ſincere Confeſſion of Chriſts Verity? truely my tongue cannot declare,<note place="margin">Example of true love and charity among the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs.</note> nor my pen expreſs the abundance of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual mirth and gladneſs, that my minde and inward man hath felt, ever ſince I heard of your hearty boldneſs, and modeſt behaviour before that bloody Butcher, in the time of all your crafty Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, eſpecially at your cruel Condemnation in their curſed Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtory place. Bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſed be God the Father of all mercy, and praiſed be his Name, for that he hath ſo graciouſly performed upon you his dear darlings, his moſt ſweet and comfortable promiſes, in not only giving you the continual ayd, ſtrength and comfort of his holy and mighty Spirit, to the faithful confeſſion of his Chriſt, for whoſe cauſe (O moſt happy men) ye are condemned to dye: but alſo in giving you ſuch a mouth and wiſdome, as all your wicked
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:180526:22"/> Enemies were not able to reſiſt,<note place="margin">The Enemies not able to withſtand the w ſedome of God in his Saints but compelled to bid them hold their peace.</note> but were fain to cry, <hi>Peace, peace,</hi> and not ſuffer you to ſpeak. As truly as God liveth (my dear Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) this is not only unto you a moſt evident probation that God is on our ſide, and a ſure certainty of your everlaſting Salvation in him; but alſo to your cruel Adverſaries (or rather Gods curſed Enemies) a plain demonſtration of their juſt eternal woe and damnation, which they ſhall be full ſure ſhortly to feel, when ye ſhall full ſweetly poſſeſs the place of felicity and pleaſure prepared for you from the beginning.</p>
            <p>Therefore (my dearly beloved) ceaſe not ſo long as ye be in this life, to praiſe the Lord with a luſty courage, for that of his great mercy and infinite goodneſs, he hath vouched you worthy this great dignity, to ſuffer for his ſake, not onely the loſs of goods, Wife and Children, long impriſonment, and cruel oppreſſion, &amp;c. but alſo the very deprivation of this mortal life, with the diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of your bodies in the fire. The which in the greateſt promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that God can bring you or any other unto in this vale of miſery; yea, ſo great an honour, as the higheſt Angel in Heaven is not permitted to have: and yet hath the Lord (for his dear Son Chriſts ſake) reputed you worthy of the ſame, yea and that before me and many other which have both long looked and longed for the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>John Careles</hi> longeth to dye a Martyr in the Goſpels cauſe.</note>Ah my moſt dear Brother <hi>Tyms,</hi> whoſe time reſteth altogether in the hands of the Lord, in a full happy time cameſt thou into this troubleſome world, but in a much more bleſſed hou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhalt thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part forth of the ſame: ſo that the ſweet ſaying of <hi>Solomon,</hi> or rather of the Holy-ghoſt, ſhall be full well verified upon thee, yea and all thy faithful fellows; <hi>Better is the day of death</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>then the day of birth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 7.</note> This ſaying cannot be verified upon every man, but upon thee my dear Brother, and ſuch as thou art, <hi>whoſe death is moſt precious before God, and full dear ſhall your blood be in his ſight.</hi> Bleſſed be God for thee, my dear Brother <hi>Tyms,</hi> and bleſſed be God again that ever I knew thee, for in a moſt happy time I came firſt into thy company. Pray for me, dear Brother, pray for me, that God will once vouch me worthy of that great dignity whereunto he hath now brought you.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:180526:22"/>
            <p>Ah my loving Brother <hi>Drake,</hi> whoſe Soul draweth now nigh un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, of whom you have received the ſame,, full glad may you be that ever God gave you a life to leave for his ſake: full well will he reſtore it to you again in a thouſand fold more glorious wiſe. Praiſe God, good Brother, as you have great cauſe, and pray for me, I beſeech you, which am ſo much unworthy (ſo great are my ſins) of that great dignity whereunto the Lord hath cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led you, and the reſt of your godly Brethren; whom I beſeech you to comfort in the Lord, as you can full well: praiſed be God for his gifts, which you have heartily applied to the ſetting forth of his glory, and the commodity of his poor afflicted Church. Which thing ſhall ſurely redound to your everlaſting joy and comfort, as you ſhall moſt effectually feel or ever it be long, though the wicked of the World judge far otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>Ah mine own Hearts, and moſt dearly beloved Brethren, <hi>Cavell, Ambroſe,</hi> and both the <hi>Spurges,</hi> Bleſſed be the Lord on your be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half, and praiſed be his Name, which hath given you ſuch a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious victory. Full valiant have you ſhewed your ſelves in the Lords fight, and full faithfully in your painful ſervice. Faint not, but go on forward as you have moſt godly begun, for great ſhall your reward be at the end of this your travel. Ah my good faithful Brethren all, what ſhall I ſay, or what ſhall I write unto you, but even the ſame that good <hi>Elizabeth</hi> did ſay to her godly kinſwoman <hi>Mary,</hi> the bleſſed Mother of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Luke 1.</note> 
               <hi>Happy art thou</hi> (quoth that good woman) <hi>which haſt believed; for all things which the Lord hath spoken to thee ſhall be fulfilled.</hi> So I ſay to you (my dear hearts in the Lord) happy are ye all, yea thrice happy ſhall ye be for evermore, becauſe ye have ſtedfaſtly believed the moſt ſweet Promiſes which God the Father hath made unto you with his own mouth, in that he hath promiſed you (which are the faithful ſeed of the believing <hi>Abraham</hi>) that ye ſhall be bleſſed ever world without end. The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of God your ſweet Father, as ye do believe, ſo do ye bear record that God is true. The teſtimony whereof ye have wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily born to the world, and ſhortly will full ſurely Seal the ſame with your Blood, yea even to morrow, I do underſtand.<note place="margin">He encourageth Gods Martyrs unto their death</note> Oh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Chriſtians! Oh valiant Souldiers of the high Captain Jeſus
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:180526:23"/> Chriſt, who for your ſake hath conquered the Devil, Death, Sin and Hell, and hath given you full victory over them for evermore! Oh worthy Witneſſes, and moſt glorious Martyrs, whoſe invincible Faith hath overcome that proud, ſturdy, bragging Prince of the World, and all his wicked Army: over whom ye ſhall ſhortly tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph for evermore. Ah my ſweet hearts, the everlaſting treaſures are full ſurely laid up for you in Heaven. The immerceſſible and moſt glorious Crown of Victory is already made and prepared for you, to be ſhortly clapt upon all your happy heads. The holy Angels of your heavenly Father are already appointed to conduct your ſweet Souls into <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome: All the heavenly Hoſt rejoyceth already, for that they ſhall ſhortly receive you with joy and felicity into their bleſſed Fellowſhip. <hi>Selah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Rejoyce with double joy, and be glad my dear Brethren, for doubtleſs ye have more cauſe then can be expreſſed. But (alas) I that for my ſins am left behinde, may lye and lament with the holy Prophet,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.</note> ſaying, <hi>Woe is me, that the dayes of my joyfull reſt are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed.</hi> Ah curſed Satan, which hath cauſed me ſo ſore to offend my moſt dear loving Father, whereby my exile and baniſhment is ſo much prolonged! Oh Chriſt my Advocate, pacifie thy Fathers wrath, which I have juſtly deſerved, that he may take me home to him in his ſweet mercy! Oh that I might now come home unto thee with my bleſſed Brethren! Well, thy will (O Lord) be effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually fulfilled, for it is onely good, and turneth all things to the beſt, for ſuch as thou in thy mercies haſt choſen.</p>
            <p>And now farewell my dear Hearts, moſt happy in the Lord: I truſt in my good God yet ſhortly to ſee you in the Celeſtial City, whereof undoubtedly the Lord hath already made you free Citizens. Though ye be yet with us for a little time, your very home is in Heaven, where your treaſure doth remain with your ſweet Lord and Redeemer Jeſus Chriſt, whoſe calling you have heard with the ears of your hearts, and therefore you ſhall never come into judgement, but paſs from death to life. Your ſins ſhall never be remembred, be they never ſo many, ſo grievous or ſo great; for your Saviour hath <hi>caſt them all into the bottom of the Sea:</hi> he hath <hi>removed them from you as far as the Eaſt is from the Weſt;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.</note> and his mercy hath
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:180526:23"/> much more prevailed over you, then is diſtance between Heaven and Earth: and hath given you for an everlaſting poſſeſſion of the ſame, all his Holyneſs, Righteouſneſs, and Juſtification,<note place="margin">Triumph of Martyrs.</note> yea and the Holy Ghoſt into your hearts, wherewith ye are ſurely ſealed unto the day of Redemption, to certifie you of your eternal Election, and that ye are his true Adopted Sons, whereby ye may boldly cry unto God, <hi>Abba, dear Father,</hi> for evermore: ſo that now no creature in Heaven, Earth nor Hell ſhall be able to accuſe you before the throne of the Heavenly King. Satan is now caſt out from you: he himſelf <hi>is judged, and hath no part in you;</hi> he will once more bite you by the heel, and then he hath done,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> for at that time you ſhall ſqueeze his head through your own good Chriſt: and ſo have you final victory for evermore. In joyful triumph whereof ye ſhall ſweetly aſcend into the place of eternal reſt, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your eldeſt Brother Chriſt is gone before you, to take poſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſion for you, and to prepare your place under the holy Altar, with <hi>Cranmer, Latimer, Ridley, Rogers, Hooper, Saunders, Farrar, Taylor, Bradford, Philpot,</hi> with many other, who will be full glad of your coming, to ſee ſix more of their appointed number, that their blood may ſo much the ſooner be revenged on them that dwell on the Earth.</p>
            <p>Thus I make an end, committing you all to Gods moſt merciful defence, whoſe quarrel ye have defended, whoſe cauſe ye have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted, whoſe glory ye have ſet forth, and whoſe name ye have conſtantly confeſſed. Farewel for a while, my dear hearts in the Lord, I will make as much haſt after you as I may. All our dear Brethren ſalute you. They Pray for you, and praiſe God for you continually. <hi>Bleſſed be the dead that dye in the Lord, for they reſt from their Labours,</hi> ſaith the Holy Ghoſt,<note place="margin">Apoc. 11.</note> 
               <hi>and their works follow them.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your own <hi>John Careles,</hi> a moſt unprofitable Servant of the Lord. <hi>Pray, pray, pray.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:180526:24"/>
            <head>To Mr. <hi>Green,</hi> Mr. <hi>Whittel,</hi> and certain other Priſoners in <hi>Newgate,</hi> Condemned and ready to be burnt for the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the <hi>Lord Jeſus.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Another Letter of <hi>John Careles</hi> wherein he doth animate <hi>Green, Whittel,</hi> and the reſt of that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany unto their Martyrdome.</note>THe everlaſting peace in Jeſus Chriſt, the continual comfort of his moſt pure and holy Spirit, be with you my moſt dear and faithful Brethren and Siſters of <hi>Newgate,</hi> the Lords appointed Sheep unto the ſlaughter, to the good performance of the great and notable work of the Lord, which he hath ſo graciouſly begun in you all; that the ſame may redound to the ſetting forth of his Glory, and to the commodity of his Church, and to your own everlaſting comfort in him, <hi>So be it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ah my dear hearts, and moſt faithful Brethren and ſiſters in the Lord, what high lauds and praiſe, yea what humble and continual thanks am I bound to give to God our Father for you and on your moſt happy behalf, who ſo mightily hath magnified himſelf in you thus far forth, in giving you his holy and mighty Spirit, to the conſtant confeſſing of Chriſts verity, even to the cruel Condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and I doubt not but he will do the ſame to the death. Oh happy and bleſſed are you that ever you were born, that the Lord will vouch you worthy of this great dignity, to dye for his ſake. Doubtleſs it is the greateſt honour that God can give you in this life. Yea,<note place="margin">Apoc. 11.</note> if they be ſo bleſſed of God that dye in the Lord, as the Holy Ghoſt ſaith they be;<note place="margin">To dye in the Lord: and for the Lord.</note> how much more bleſſed and happy then are you, that dye not onely in the Lord, but alſo for the Lord? Oh that it were the good will of God, that the good hour were now come, that I might go with you! ah that my ſins made me not unworthy of ſuch an excellent dignity!</p>
            <p>Be thankful dear hearts, be thankful, and rejoyce in the Lord; for mighty is his mercy towards you, and great is your reward in Heaven, the which you like faithful perſons have plucked to you with a godly violence of an invincible Faith. Oh worthy warriers of the moſt high captain! Oh conſtant Confeſſors of the everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing verity! how glorious a Crown of victory ſhall you ſhortly receive, which is prepared for all ſuch as do continue to the end?
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:180526:24"/> Oh you ſweet Saints of the Lord, how precious ſhall your death be in his ſight? Oh how dear are your Souls to your Redeemer, in whoſe hands they ſhall moſt joyfully reſt, and the pains of death ſhall never touch you? Oh how bleſſed ſhall you be, when Chriſt ſhall appear, at the which time you ſhall receive your bodies again full of Immortality? Oh how joyful ſhall you be when Chriſt, according to his promiſe ſhall knowledge you before his Father and his holy Angels, as you have moſt conſtantly confeſſed him to be your Lord and onely Saviour before men?</p>
            <p>Oh bleſſed <hi>Green,</hi> thou meek and loving Lamb of the Lord, how happy art thou to be appointed to dye for his ſake? A full dainty diſh art thou for the Lords own tooth, Freſh and Green ſhalt thou be in the houſe of the Lord, and thy fruits ſhall never wither nor decay. Although thou go here forth ſowing thy good fruits with Tears, the time ſhall come that thou ſhalt reap with joy and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the fruits of everlaſting life, and that without ceaſing. Be merry therefore, and <hi>fear not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 12.</note> 
               <hi>for it is thy Fathers will to give thee a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> whereunto he hath choſen thee before the foundations of the World were laid.</p>
            <p>Oh happy Miniſter, thou man of God, how glad mayeſt thou be of Gods gracious favour, which hath prevented thee in the day of thy tryal? Oh happy <hi>Peter,</hi> whoſe part thou haſt well played; therefore thy reward and portion ſhall be like unto his. Now haſt thou good experience of mans infirmity, but much more proof and taſte, yea ſenſe and feeling of Gods abundant bottomleſs mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. Although <hi>Satan deſired to ſift thee,</hi> yet Chriſt thy good Captain, <hi>prayed that thy Faith ſhould not fail.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Gods ſtrength is made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect by thy weakneſs, and his grace is ſufficient for thee his dear Childe. Thine Example did ſo incourage and ſtrengthen thy poor Brethren, that God is every way glorified by thee, and ſhortly will he glorifie thee with himſelf, with that glory which he hath prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for thee his Elect darling before the World was made. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore rejoyce and be glad, for thou haſt good occaſion, in finding ſuch favour in his fight.</p>
            <p>This is moſt true (oh my other Brethren, whom I do not know, neither have I heard much of you) happy are you that ever you
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:180526:25"/> were born, and bleſſed be our God which hath given you ſuch Victory over the bloody Beaſt. Shortly ſhall you be clothed in large white garments,<note place="margin">Apoc. 19.</note> and fine rayneſs of Righteouſneſs, and ſo ſhall you follow the Lamb on Mount Sion with new Songs of Mirth and Melody, for your delivery forth of Satans Power and tyranny. God for evermore be bleſſed for you, and ſtrengthen you to the end, as I doubt not but he will: for he never failed them that put their truſt in him.</p>
            <p>Oh my dear and faithful ſiſter <hi>Joane Warner,</hi> what ſhall I ſay to thee? Thy tryal hath been great; thy Victory in Chriſt hath been notable, thou haſt overcome many a ſharp ſhower and ſtorm: ſhortly ſhalt thou arrive at the Haven of quiet reſt, and receive a reward due to a conſtant Martyr. Thou ſhalt go home to thy Heavenly Father, and poſſeſs for ever the inheritance which Chriſt hath purchaſed for thee, where thy earthly Parents be, ſtill looking for thee, which have triumphed over Antichriſt moſt victoriouſly. Oh bleſſed Parents of happy Children, which have ſhewed ſuch an example, as the like hath been ſeldome ſeen. I ſalute thee dear Siſter of like conſtant minde; whoſe conſtant example is worthy of continual memory. Praiſed be God for you mine own ſweet ſiſters,<note place="margin">Mat. 25.</note> which hath made you to play ſuch wiſe Virgins parts. He hath plentifully poured the oyle of his Spirit into the Lamps of your Faith, ſo that the light hereof ſhall never be extinct. You ſhall enter with your Bridegroom into everlaſting joy, whereunto you were choſen in him from the beginning.</p>
            <p>Oh my dear Brethren and ſiſters, you bleſſed Saints of the Lord, how much and how deeply am I bound to praiſe God for you both day and night? Pray, pray for me (my dear hearts) for the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der mercy of God, that I may be made worthy to follow your trace. Oh that I had run the race of my life as far as you have done yours,<note place="margin">John 5.</note> and were as nigh my journeys end as you be unto yours. But alas, I lye like the lame man at the Pooles ſide by <hi>Solomons Porch,</hi> and every man goeth into the place of health before me: But God will appoint me one, one day to put me in. I truſt my Lord of <hi>London</hi>'s Colehouſe is empty, and all his Officers idle: therefore they muſt ſhortly fetch more ſheep to the ſhambles; for
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:180526:25"/> he is the common ſlaughter-ſlave of all <hi>England.</hi>
               <note place="margin">B. <hi>Bonner</hi> called the ſlaughter ſlave of <hi>England</hi>
               </note> But happy are you that are paſſed through the Pikes, and delivered out of his hands, and from all the Angels of the Darkneſs of this World, which long tempted you in the Wilderneſs of the ſame: but now ſhall the Angels of God come and miniſter unto you, for they are your Servants to hold you up in their hands, that you ſhall not hurt your foot, no nor one hair of your head ſhall periſh. They ſhall carry you up to heaven in a fiery Chariot,<note place="margin">Pſal 60. 2 King 2.</note> though you leave your Mantle behinde you for a time, till God reſtore the ſame to you again in a more ample and glorious ſort.</p>
            <p>Thus in haſte, (as it doth appear,) I am conſtrained to make an end, committing you all to Gods moſt merciful defence: who ever have you in his bleſſed keeping; deſiring you all to remember me in your godly and faithful Prayers, as I will not forget you in mine, by Gods grace. The bleſſing of God be with you all, my dear Brethren and ſiſters. All our Brethren and fellow-priſoners here have them moſt heartily commended unto you, and pray for you without ceaſing. God ſend us a merry meeting in his Kingdome. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>By your Brother and unfeigned lover, <hi>John Careles</hi> Priſoner, abiding his moſt merciful will and pleaſure. <hi>Pray, pray, pray.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>To my faithful and loving Brother, <hi>W. Tyms,</hi> Priſoner in <hi>Newgate.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe Everlaſting peace of God in Ieſus Chriſt, with the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all joy, comfort and ſtrength of his ſweet Spirit be multiplied, and daily more and more increaſed in your good heart (my moſt faithful and dear Brother <hi>Tyms,</hi>) to the full quieting of your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and beating back of all the fiery darts of the wicked, that you may ſhortly receive the glorious Crown of Victory, and in the ſame triumph over all your Enemies for evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I cannot expreſs the exceeding great joy and conſolation of my poor heart, conſidering the marvellous works of God moſt graciouſly wrought upon you not onely in proving you, and trying
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:180526:26"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:180526:26"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:180526:27"/> your Faith by his great and huge Croſſes both inwardly and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, but alſo in giving you ſo great Conſolation and Conſtancy in the midſt of the ſame. Faithful is God, and true of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes,<note place="margin">Gods Children never tempted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove their ſtrength.</note> who hath ſaid, <hi>That he will never ſuffer his choſen children to be tempted above their ſtrength, but in the midſt of their temptation will make an out-ſcape for them,</hi> by ſuch means as may make to his glory and their everlaſting conſolation. My dear heart, great cauſe have you to be of good comfort, for I ſee in you as lively a token of Gods everlaſting love and favour in Jeſus Chriſt, as ever I perceived in any man: in reſpect whereof I do even with my heart love, honour and reverence you, beſeeching God for his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Name ſake, in the Bowels and Blood of our Lord and onely Saviour Jeſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">He confirmeth <hi>W. Tims</hi> being condemned to the day of his Martyrdome.</note> to finiſh his good work in you, as I doubt not but he will do, according to his infallible Promiſes: yea, I am well aſſured thereof, foraſmu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h as you have ſo effectually received his holy Spirit into your heart, as a pledg and ſure Seal of your eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Redemption, and a Teſtimony of your Adoption in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus. For which cauſe Satan ſo ſore envieth you, that he hath now bent all his fierce Ordnance againſt you, thinking thereby utterly to deſtroy the invincible Fort of your Faith, founded moſt firmly upon the unmoveable Rock CHRIST, againſt the which, the Devil, Sin, nor yet Hell gates ſhall never prevail. <hi>Selah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore, mine own Bowels in the Lord, be not diſcomforted for this your Conflict, which doubtleſs ſhall greatly increaſe your Crown of Glory, Triumph and Victory: but take a good heart un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, and buckle boldly with Satan, both in himſelf and in his ſubtile Members.<note place="margin">It is the nature of Gods Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to be temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> It is the very divine Ordinance of God, that all his regenerate Children ſhall be tempted, proved and tryed: as we ſee by the Example of our Saviour Chriſt, who as ſoon as he was Baptized was ſtraightwayes led of the Holy Ghoſt into the Wilderneſs, there to be tempted of the Devil. But there got he ſuch a glorious victory over Satan, that he could never ſince finally prevail againſt any of his poor Members, but in every aſſault that he maketh either inwardly or outwardly, he getteth a foyle, and taketh ſhame: ſo that now he rageth with all the ſpight poſſible, ſpecially
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:180526:27"/> becauſe he knoweth his time is but ſhort.<note place="margin">James 4.</note> St. <hi>James</hi> teſtifieth that he is but a very Coward, that will ſoon flie, if he be faithfully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted. And as for his tempting Tools, the Lord hath made them manifeſt unto us, ſo that he cannot deceive us, though he aſſault us;<note place="margin">Satans tempting tools. 2 Cor. 2.</note> for as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>his very thoughts are not unknown unto us,</hi> as it doth in you largely appear, praiſed be the Lords Name therefore.</p>
            <p>You ſee, dear Brother, that now to moleſt you and ſuch as you are, that be even paſſing from this Vale of Miſery, he hath but two wayes, or two pieces of Ordnance to ſhoot at you,<note place="margin">Two principal pellets of Satan whereby he aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ulteth Gods Servants. 1. Fear of ſin and death, and Infidelity of Gods promiſes. Remedy againſt Fear and Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity.</note> with the which he cannot hurt you, becauſe you have two bulwarks to defend you. The firſt of theſe terrible Guns that Satan hath ſhot at you, is the very ſame that he continually ſhooteth at me, that is to ſay, <hi>Fear</hi> and <hi>Infidelity;</hi> for the uglyſomneſs of death, and horrour of my ſins, which be ſo many, grievous and great: but this Pellet is eaſily put away with the ſurer ſhield of Faith in the moſt precious death and bloodſhedding of our dear Lord and onely Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, whom the Father hath given unto us wholy to be ours for <hi>evermore, and with him hath given us all things,</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith: So that though we be never ſo great ſinners, yet Chriſt is made unto us Holyneſs, Righteouſneſs, and juſtification. He hath clothed us with all his Merits, Mercies and moſt ſweet ſufferings, and hath taken unto him all our miſery, wretchedneſs, ſin and infirmity. So that if any ſhould now be condemned for the ſame, it muſt needs be Ieſus Chriſt, which hath taken them upon him. But indeed he hath made ſatiſfaction for them to the uttermoſt jot; ſo that for his ſake they ſhall never be imputed to us, if they were a Thouſand times ſo many moe as they be. This do you moſt effectually feel and know, dear Brother, a great deal better then I can tell you, bleſſed be God therefore.</p>
            <p>And now Satan, ſeeing he cannot prevail with his boiſterous Battery againſt this Bulwark of Faith, which doth ſo quench all his fiery darts, that they can do you no harm, but rather do you good ſervice, to caſt you down under the mighty hand of God,<note place="margin">The ſecond pel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let of Satan is confidence and truſt in our own good works.</note> that he may take you up by his onely grace and power, and ſo you may render him all the glory by Ieſus Chriſt (which thing the Enemy cannot abide in no wiſe) therefore he ſhooteth off his other Piece
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:180526:28"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:180526:28"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:180526:29"/> moſt peſtilent, to provoke you to put ſome part of your truſt and confidence in your ſelf, and in your own holineſs and righteouſneſs, that you might that way rob God of his glory, Chriſt of his honour and dignity of his death.<note place="margin">Remedy againſt the ſecond Pel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let.</note> But bleſſed be the Lord God, you have alſo a full ſtrong Bulwark to beat back this peſtiferous Pellet alſo, even the pure Law of God, which proveth the beſt of us all damnable ſinners in the ſight of God, if he would enter into judgement with us according to the ſeverity of the ſame, and that even our beſt works are polluted and defiled in ſuch ſort,<note place="margin">Iſay. 64.</note> as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet deſcribeth them. With which manner of ſpeaking, our free-will Phariſees are much offended, for it felleth all mans Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs to the ground, (I had like to have ſaid, to the bottom of Hell) and extolleth onely the Righteouſneſs of Jeſus Chriſt, which is allowed before God, and is freely given to all thoſe that firmly believe, as bleſſed be God you do.</p>
            <p>Ah my good brother <hi>Tyms,</hi> Satan hath put his hand in a wrong box when he beginneth to tempt you, either to Vain-glory or miſtruſt: for you are an old beaten ſouldier, and have had good experience of theſe manner of Temptations, both by your ſelf and other, whom you know well were the beloved of God.<note place="margin">Satan overcome in Gods Saints.</note> Be of good chear therefore, dear heart, be of good chear, for now Satan hath wrought all his malice: he hath done all that he can, and hath ſhot off all his laſt Pieces, wherewith he had thought to have done moſt miſchief; but now he ſeeth he cannot prevail, (the ſtrong Tower of your Faith being ſo invincible) he will pluck up all his Tents, and get him to ſome other place to practiſe the like aſſaults: and then will the Angels of God come and miniſter unto you the moſt ſweet and heavenly Conſolations of the holy Ghoſt. To him therefore who is able to do exceeding abundantly above all that ever we can deſire or think, I do moſt heartily commit you, with all the reſt of your Godly Priſon-fellows, who comfort, ſtrengthen, and defend you with his grace, &amp; mighty operation of his holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, as he hath hitherto done, that you having a moſt glorious Victory over the ſubtile Serpent and all his wicked ſeed, may alſo receive the Crown of Glory and Immortality, prepared for you before the foundations of the World were laid, and is ſo ſurely kept for
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:180526:29"/> you in the hands of him who is infallible, that the Devil, Sin, Death or Hell ſhall never be able to deprive you of the ſame. The bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God be with you now and for evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi> Pray, pray, pray for me.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your own for ever, <hi>John Careles.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>To my good Siſter, Mrs. <hi>Cotton.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe Peace of God in Jeſus Chriſt, the eternall Comforts of his ſweet Spirit, be with you my dear and faithfull Siſter, to the full accompliſhment of that good work which he hath moſt graciouſly begun in you, that the ſame may be effectuall to the ſetting forth of his glory, and to your everlaſting Conſolation in him. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My loving and faithfull Siſter in the Lord, I thank you for all your loving kindneſs ſhewed unto me, but especially for your godly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of me in your fervent and faithfull Prayers, and for your moſt godly and comfortable Letter, whereby you do not onely much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe my joy and comfort, but alſo put me in remembrance of my duty towards you.</p>
            <p>Bleſſed be the Lord our God,<note place="margin">Gods great gift in women.</note> which of his great mercy hath ſo beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified his Church in theſe dayes, that even unto many godly women he hath given moſt excellent gifts of knowledge and underſtanding of his Truth, ſo that they are not onely well able to inform their own Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in all things neceſſary to Salvation, but alſo moſt ſweetly to comfort their ſorrowfull Brethren and Siſters that ſuſtain any trouble for the Teſtimony of Gods Truth; yea, and that which is more, even in the middeſt of their great Conflicts of Conſcience. Of which moſt happy number of godly and virtuous women, my dear heart, you are one, and that of the chiefeſt, being plentifully endued with the gifts of Gods moſt gracious Spirit, as it doth full well appear in your daily doings: God onely have the praiſe therefore.</p>
            <p>Foraſmuch then as God hath given you the gift to write,<note place="margin">Note how God ſometime giveth comfort by wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker veſſels.</note> I ſhall moſt heartily deſire you to let me hear from you ſometimes, be it never ſo little, for truly I t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke great Comfort and Courage thereby, specially in
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:180526:30"/> my poor Conſcience, which is ſore aſſaulted of ſubtile Satan, and in a manner oppreſſed of my ſin. Pray, dear S ſter, that God may give me true, hearty, and earneſt Repentance, and increaſe my Faith, for they are both the good gifts of God onely, and farre paſs the reach of my power, to take at my pleaſure.</p>
            <p>Therefore, dear Siſter, if you w ll help me to beg the ſame of our dear loving Father, I am ſure that he both can and will g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve them me in his good time. And as for the fear of Death, or terrour of the Fire, I moſt heartily thank my good God I feel it not: onely it is mine own ſins and unthankefulneſs which holdeth hard battel, and wageth ſtrong warre againſt me, which onely goeth about to ſeparate me from my good Captain Chriſt, that I ſhould not enjoy his glorious victory; but God being on my ſide, (as I am ſure he is) that cannot continually prev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>il againſt me. Though God for a time permit Satan to take his pleaſure on me, as he did upon <hi>Job,</hi> yet I doubt not but in the end all ſhall turn to my profit, through the Merits of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, To whoſe moſt mercifull defence I commit you, dear Siſter, with all the reſt of the Lords Elect. Farewell in Chriſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your unfeignedly, <hi>John Careles. Pray, pray, pray, pray.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>To my dear Brother, <hi>T. V.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe everlaſting peace of God in Jeſus Chriſt, the continual Comforts of his moſt pure and holy Spirit, be with you my moſt dear friend and faithful Brother <hi>V.</hi> to the increaſe of your Faith, and comfort of your ſorrowful Spirit, which is to the Father a ſweet Sacrifice through Chriſt: for whoſe ſake he will never deſpiſe your humble and contrite heart, but doth favourably accept the ſame, and will in moſt ample wiſe perform the deſire thereof to his Glory, and your eternal Comfort in him.</p>
            <p>In the mids of my manifold Croſſes and Troubles, wherein I am conſtrained to flee unto God for refuge and ſuccour by earneſt and faithful Prayer, I cannot forget you (my dear heart in the Lord)
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:180526:30"/> but eſteeming your ſtate for mine own, I do pour forth my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint for y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u, as I do for my ſelf, and rather more, as I think pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent need doth require, deſiring moſt heartily to hear of the good ſucceſs of the ſame in y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u. The Lord God for his mercy ſake accompliſh my deſi e as I doubt not but he will, when he ſeeth it good, and moſt to his glory, and to your comfort and commodity. O that I might once ſee you ſo merry in Chriſt,<note place="margin">Pſal. 57.</note> as you have juſt cauſe to be, that you might ſay with <hi>David, Awake my glory, awake lute and harp, bring forth the pſaltery with the merry ſong, that I might ſing a new ſong of praiſe and thanksgiving unto the Lord, for the light of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable countenance, his help and deliverance.</hi> Oh!<note place="margin">Pſal. 45.</note> that would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh me as a moſt precious Oyle, and gladden my poor heart, which is aſſaulted with ſorrow moe wayes then one.<note place="margin">Comfort for a ſick Conſcience.</note> I doubt not but the ſame ſhall by your means receive much comfort, though for a time it doth mourn with you, that we may be made both glad together, yea and that with ſuch gladneſs as ſhall continue for ever.</p>
            <p>But in the mean ſpace (I ſay) moſt happy are you,<note place="margin">Mat. 9.</note> that ſo heartily mourn the abſence of the Bridegroom. If you were not a wedding-childe you could never do it. Onely Chriſts true Diſciples do mourn for his abſence; therefore ſhall they doubtleſs rejoyce at his preſence, which will be ſo much more joyful, by how much the abſence is more ſorrowful.</p>
            <p>Therefore, my good Brother, take a good heart unto you, and be of good chear: Say with the Prophet <hi>David, O my Soul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 42.</note> 
               <hi>why art thou ſo heavy, and why art thou ſo diſquieted within me? O put thy truſt in God, for I will yet give him thanks for the help of his loving countenance, and becauſe he is my God.</hi> Read the 41 &amp; 42 <hi>Pſalm</hi> for your comfort, and conſider that the holy King and Prophet, at the making and firſt ſaying of them, was even in the ſame caſe that you are now in; but he ſtill comforted himſelf with the ſweet promiſes of God: and ſo do you, my dear heart, for to you they do as well pertain, as they did to him, and as ſurely ſhall they be performed upon you, as they were upon him; for he is one God and dear Father unto you both and for his Mercy, Truth and Promiſe ſake,<note place="margin">Gods love goeth not by our deſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vings, but by Faith in Jeſus.</note> he muſt needs make good unto you all that he hath ſaid.</p>
            <p>If his love toward you ſtood in reſpect of your own merit and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:180526:31"/> worthineſs, you might well mourn, lament and complain; yea, you had good cauſe to doubt, fear and miſtruſt: but ſeeing he loveth you onely for and in Jeſus Chriſt, who is your whole Holineſs, Righteouſneſs and Redemption, lay away all mourning, lament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and complaining; baniſh from you all fear, miſtruſt and infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and know that as long as Chriſt doth continue Gods Son, ſo long muſt the love of the Father continue towards you immutable, and his good will unchangeable, and cannot be altered through any of your infirmities. For this is moſt true, that as long as the Cauſe of any thing doth laſt, ſo long muſt the Effect remain; but Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s the whole Cauſe why the Father loveth you, and he alſo continueth for ever:<note place="margin">Chriſt onely is the cauſe why his Father lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us.</note> Then muſt I needs conclude, that the love of the Father continueth towards you for ever, and (as the Pſalmiſt moſt joyful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo often ſingeth) <hi>His mercy endureth for ever and ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is moſt true, mine own dear heart, although the Lord for a time hide it from your ſenſes, that you might be the more earneſt in Prayer to him for the feeling of it, and alſo the more thankfull for it when he doth give the lively taſte of it,<note place="margin">Why God ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time hideth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from us.</note> as doubtleſs he will do ere ever it be long; and then ſhall you be well able to comfort other in the ſame ſtate that you are now in, with the ſame comfort where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with you are and further ſhall be comforted of God.</p>
            <p>Therefore lift up your hands that are now a little fallen down, and ſtretch forth the weak knees of your troubled minde,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.</note> which now mourneth with a godly mourning, and therefore ſhall it be full well comforted with that ſweet peace of God which paſſeth all underſtanding, and you are ſure already to enjoy the bleſſing that Chriſt gave unto the godly mourners of Sion upon the mount,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 7.</note> at the firſt Sermon that he made. O happy <hi>V.</hi> in whoſe mourning company I had rather be, then in the houſe of mirth and banquetting of ſuch as ſee not what cauſe they have to mourn and be ſorry.<note place="margin">Meaſure ought to be in mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> But yet my good Brother, uſe a meaſure in this your godly mourning, and make not your faithful Friends too much ſorry for you. Let the perſwaſions of ſuch godly lovers as you do daily company withal, or rather the perſwaſions of the holy Ghoſt by them, move you to ſome godly mirth and rejoycing. Conſider that you are commanded by the mouth of Saint <hi>Paul</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 4.</note>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:180526:31"/> thereto <hi>Rejoyce in the Lord</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and I ſay again Rejoyce.</hi> Mark how he doubleth the Sentence, that we may perceive it is a moſt earneſt and neceſſary thing he requireth. Obey the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God in this behalf: wherein as you cannot but highly pleaſe him, ſo I aſſure you,<note place="margin">Example of Chriſtian Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on towards his afflicted Brother</note> you ſhall very much rejoyce my poor heart, and the hearts of other which pray for you with mourning tears, and make that cruel enemy Satan, and all your adverſaries ſorry, which will rejoyce and laugh to ſee you mourn. Oh my good Brother, let it manifeſtly appear that the Lord of his great mercy hath hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d our faithful and hearry requeſts for you. Oh how would that rejoyce me in the mids of my troubles?</p>
            <p>Therefore now to conclude, becauſe the darkneſs conſtraineth me to make an end for this time, I ſay my dear and faithful Brother <hi>V.</hi> in reſpect of the great cauſe you have of your own part through Chriſt, and for the glory and honour of almighty God, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, joy and rejoycing of your dear Brethren and Siſters in Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt, alſo your own duety by the Commandment of God, and laſt of all to vex, moleſt and grieve Satan withal, Rejoyce in the Lord, and be moſt heartily glad in him, who is wholly yours, and you are his, and ſhall be for evermore. <hi>Selah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Farewel mine own Bowels in the Lord, and praiſe God with joyful lips and a merry heart, and pray for me his moſt unprofitable Servant, which have more cauſe, concerning my ſelf, to lament then any one man living: but my good bridegroom is preſent, and bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth me caſt away my mourning garments, and therefore I muſt needs be merry with him; and ſo he biddeth you to be by my mouth, for he is preſent with you, although for ſorrow you cannot know him, as <hi>Magdalen</hi> could not in the garden, until he ſpake unto her. The Lord God ſpeak theſe words of comfort in your heart, and open the eyes of your minde, that you may perfectly perceive and feel his bleſſed preſence, and ſo rejoyce in the ſame for evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi> Comfort your heart in Chriſt, and caſt your care upon him, for he careth for you.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Brother in the Lord, abiding his good pleaſure, <hi>John Careles.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:180526:32"/>
            <head>To my dear and faithful Brother, <hi>Auguſtine Bernher.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe peace of God in Jeſus Chriſt, the help, comfort and aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of his eternal Spirit, be with you my dear and faithful Brother <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and with all the reſt of my good Brethren and Siſters of the houſes of <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xterly</hi> and <hi>Manceter,</hi> (which mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for the miſery of Gods People) to your everlaſting Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in him. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Right glad I am to hear my dear and faithful Brother <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) that God of his great mercy and infinite goodneſs, hath yet ſo graciouſly delivered and preſerved you out of your enemies hands, beſeeching Almighty God alſo, from the bottom of my heart, to be your continual defence unto the end as hitherto he hath moſt graciouſly been, that you may live and dye both to Gods Glory, the commodity of his Church, and to the increaſe of your own everlaſting joy and comfort in him.</p>
            <p>Know you dear Brother, that I have received your Letter, for the which, I heartily thank you. Indeed I think it very ſhort, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it ſeemeth ſomething ſharply to rebuke me in the beginning for the breach of my promiſe, in not writing to you of this long time. Well Brother, I am content to bear it with patience, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that you are troubled otherwiſe (the Lord comfort you and all heavy hearts) neither will I ſpend Ink and Paper for my purgation in this point. God be knoweth whether I be ſo mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs of my promiſe, as it appeareth in your ſight I am. Your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt I will truly perform to the uttermoſt of my power, as gladly as any poor wretch ſhall do in the World, and I thank God I have done no leſs of long time. And as my poor Prayer ſhall be a handmaid to wait upon you which way ſoever you ride or go; ſo I beſeech you that my ſimple counſel may take ſome place in you, in this time of your pilgrimage, which you paſs in no ſmall peril: God keep and preſerve you for his Names ſake.<note place="margin">He counſelleth <hi>Auguſtine</hi> to be circumſpect, &amp; not raſhly to thruſt himſelf in danger.</note> I do not diſallow, but much praiſe and commend your hearty boldneſs in putting your ſelf in preaſe, when any one of Gods People needeth your help in any point. But yet I would not have you thruſt your ſelf in danger,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:180526:32"/> when you can do them no good, or at leaſt wiſe when they may well enough ſpare that good you would do them: for if you ſhould then chance to be taken you ſhall not onely be no comfort unto them, but alſo a great diſcomfort, adding ſorrow unto their ſorrow.</p>
            <p>I do not perſwade you to abſent your ſelf from any place <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>here your preſence of neceſſity is required: for in all ſuch pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, I know, God will preſerve you, as he hath hithe to wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully done, praiſed be his Name therefore: or if it ſhall pleaſe him to permit you in any ſuch place to be taken, I know he will moſt ſweetly comfort your Conſcience with this conſideration, That it is the very Providence and Appointment of God, that you ſhould there and then be taken up for a Witneſs of his Truth unto the world: But I cannot allow, nor be contented that you ſhould raſhly or negligently thruſt your ſelf into that place where your wicked enemies do continually haunt, yea and lay wait for you, when no neceſſity of your ſelf, nor of any other of Gods people, doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire your company. If they need any of your godly counſel you may write unto them that thing that you think good; which (I dare ſay) will be ſufficient unto them. For (continuall thanks and praiſes be given unto the Everlaſting God) there is none of thoſe that be cruelly condemn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d for Gods Truth, that now be weaklings: for they have manfully paſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d through the Pikes, and they have boldly abidden the brunt of the Battel, and therefore I reckon the worſt is paſt with them already: So that now and then a godly Letter from you to them ſhall do as much good as your company ſhall do, and perchance more too; for writing ſticketh longer in the memory then word do: yea, though your Letters were as ſhort to them, as your laſt was to me, ſo that the ſame be ſomething ſweeter, and not all thing ſo ſharp.</p>
            <p>This (dear Brother) is the ſimple counſel which I would gladly have you obſerve, partly for that I heartily pray for your preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to the commodity of Chriſts Church, and partly for that I unfeignedly w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh the peace, comfort and tranquility of your own Conſcience, which I know will be quickly ready to accuſe you,<note place="margin">A good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is ſoon troubled.</note> if you do any thing wherein you have not the Word of God for your
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:180526:33"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:180526:33"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:180526:34"/> warrant. For in a glaſs that is clear, a ſmall mote will ſoon ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear: even ſo the good Conſcience of Gods choſen children be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more clear then Chryſtal, will quickly accuſe them at the leaſt fault they do commit, whereas the wicked worldlings have their Conſcience ſo clogged and corrupted through the cuſtome of ſin, that they cannot ſee nor perceive their own ſhameful deeds and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked works, until God ſet the ſame before them for their utter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtruction, and then deſpair they immediately. But ſeeing that God hath given you a clear Conſcience, and a pure, ſharp, quick, and lively ſight in your Soul, I would wiſh you to beware that you do nothing unadviſedly,<note place="margin">Conſcience of ſin is ſometimes taken where none is commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> but upon a good ground: for an accuſing Conſcience is a ſore thing when death doth approach, and then Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan will not ſtick to tell you that you have too much tempted God, when peradventure you have done nothing ſo at all For this cauſe (I ſay) partly I have thought it good to admoniſh you (as I have done often) to be circumſpect, according to the counſel of Chriſt, which biddeth you to beware of men.<note place="margin">Matth. 10.</note> Other things I have not to write, for I know this Bearer can certifie you of all things at large, better then I can declare it by writing.</p>
            <p>I beſeech you, good <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> help me forward by your hearty Prayers, for I truſt I have but a ſmall time in this troubleſome World: Dr. <hi>Story</hi> told our Marſhal, that we ſhould all be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched ſo ſoon as he came from <hi>Oxford,</hi> whither he and other bloody Butchers be gone to make ſlaughter of Chriſts ſheep that lye there appointed to be ſlain. God for Chriſts ſake put them and ſuch like beſides their cruel purpoſe, if it be his good w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; Amen good Lord. I pray you do my moſt hearty commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to my good Siſter and faithful Friend, good Mris. <hi>Mary Glover:</hi> I beſeech God be her comfort, as I doubt not but he is. I am very glad to hear that ſhe doth ſo joyfully and ſo patiently bear this great Croſs that God hath laid upon her. I pray God ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then her, and all other his dear Saints unto the end. <hi>Amen.</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend me unto my dear and faithful Siſter <hi>Elizabeth B.</hi> I thank her moſt heartily for her Napkin, and ſo I do you dear Brother for my ſhirt. Truly that day that we were appointed to come to our An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer before the Commiſſioners (which had ſent word the ſame
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:180526:34"/> morning, that they would come to the Kings Bench by eight of the clock, and the houſe, and all things were trimmed and made ready for them) I got that Shirt on my back and that Napkin in my hand,<note place="margin">The Chriſtian courage of <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hn Careles.</hi>
               </note> and me thought that they did help to harneſs me and weapon me well, to go fight againſt that Bloody Beaſt of Babylon. And truſt me truly, if they had come, I would have ſtricken three ſtrokes the more for your two ſakes, as well as God would have abled me to have ſet them on, as by Gods grace I will not fail to do at the next Skirmiſh that I come to: wherefore I pray you pray for me, that I may be ſtrong and hardy to lay on good load. Oh that I might ſo ſtrike him down, that he ſhould never be able for to riſe again. But that ſtroke belongeth onely to the Lord, to ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ike at his coming, the which I truſt will be ſhortly? Oh haſten it good Lord, and ſhorten theſe ſorrowful and ſinful dayes, for thy great mercies ſake.</p>
            <p>Farewel my dear and faithful loving Brother: The Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d defend, keep and preſerve you from the power of your Enemies v ſible and inviſible, and ſend us a moſt joyful and merry meeting here or elſwhere, as it ſhall pleaſe his goodneſs to appoint us. In the mean ſpace I ſhall moſt earneſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y deſire you to pray for me, for I never had more need in my life: and doubtleſs you ſhall never want my poor prayer, if it ſhall pleaſe God to accept the Prayer of ſo ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful a wretch as I am The Lord impute not my ſins to me, for Ieſus Chriſts ſake, unto whoſe moſt merciful defence, I do moſt heartily commit you. The bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſing of God be with you now and ever. <hi>Amen.</hi> I pray you do my moſt hearty commendations to Mr. <hi>John Glover:</hi> I do not forget him in my daily Prayers, and I truſt he doth Remember me.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your poor Brother, alwayes mindful of you in my Prayer, <hi>John Careles,</hi> Priſoner, abiding Gods pleaſure.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:180526:35"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:180526:35"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:180526:36"/>
            <head>To my dear Brother <hi>Henry Adlington,</hi> Priſoner in the <hi>Lollards Tower.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe everlaſting peace of God in Ieſus Chriſt, the continual ayd, ſtrength, joy and comfort of his moſt pure, holy and mighty Spirit with the increaſe of Faith and lively feeling of his Mercies, be moſt eff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctuouſly wrought in your heart, my dear and faithful loving Brother <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ingto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and in the hearts of all your other godly Priſon fellows, to the full finiſhing of that good work which the Lord hath moſt graciouſly begun in you, that the ſame may be to the ſetting forth of his glory, the commodity of his poor affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Church, and to your own eternal joy and comfort in him. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My moſt dear and faithful loving Brother in our Lord, I with all the reſt of my loving Brethren here with me, do moſt humbly and heartily commend us unto you, with all faithful Remembrance of you in our daily prayers, giving God earneſt thanks on your moſt happy behalf, for that he hath given you ſuch hearty boldneſs and Chriſtian conſtancy in the faithful confeſſion of his everlaſting Verity. Bleſſed be God for thee, my dearly beloved Brother, which hath vouched thee worthy of ſo great a dignity, as to ſuffer for his ſake, and the ſetting forth of his glory. Oh glad in heart mayeſt thou be, to whom it is given, not onely to believe in thy Lord and Chriſt moſt lively; but alſo to ſuffer for his ſake, as one of his ſilly ſheep appointed to the ſlaughter. Be of good com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort therefore my good Brother, for your Calling unto the Croſs of Chriſt, was after a marvellous ſort: ſurely it was onely the Lords appointment, and therefore he will well perform his own work in and upon you to the great magnifying of his glory, and comfort of your Brethren, whoſe hearts are mightily refreſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, to hear how heartily you have behaved your ſelf hitherto. This preſent day I received a letter from you, at the reading whereof my Brethren and I were not a little comforted, to ſee your Conſcience ſo quieted in Chriſt, and your continuance ſo ſtedfaſt in him: which things be the ſpecial gifts of God, not given unto every man, but to you his
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:180526:36"/> dear darling, Elect, and choſen in Chriſt, and ſuch as you be. And whereas you do require to know my ſimple minde concerning your anſwer unto Dr. <hi>Story</hi> and the Chancellor: Truly I ſay you did anſwer them very well; for there are but two Sacraments indeed, that is to ſay, the Sacrament of Baptiſm, and the Sacrament of the Body and Blood of Chriſt, as you have full well anſwered them: Praiſed be God for his good gifts, who chuſeth the weak, to confound the ſtrong, and the fooliſh to confound the worldly wiſe. If when you come before them again, they do aſk you what a Sacrament is; ſay you, That a Sacrament, being miniſtred accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Chriſts Inſtitution, is a viſible Sign of an inviſible Grace,<note place="margin">What a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is.</note> and hath the promiſe of Gods Mercy annexed unto it, available to all ſuch as do worthily receive it, and not unworthily worſhip it: as they would have us to do, contrary to Gods Commandment. And theſe properties belonging to Chriſts true Sacraments, cannot be applyed to any one of thoſe five Sacraments which they have invented of their own brain, ſince Antichriſt began to reign, to blinde the people withal.</p>
            <p>I perceive dear heart, that upon Friday they do intend to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn you, and to give you your Judgement. Therefore I think they w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll have no great reaſoning with you, but bid you anſwer them directly, either Yea, or Nay, to all ſuch things as they have to charge you withal, which they have gathered of you ſince you came into their cruel hands. But if they will needs make many words with you, becauſe you are but a ſimple man, and therefore perchance they will be the buſier with you to trouble you with many queſtions, to cumber your knowledge, and then ſeem to triumph over you, and that truth that you do hold: if (I ſay) they do this (as perhaps for ſome evil purpoſe they will) then be you ſo plain and ſhort as you can, ſaying roundly unto them theſe or ſuch like words, as nigh as you can.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Be it known unto you, that I in all points do believe as it becometh a true Chriſtian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">He inſtructeth him how, and what to Anſwer to the adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</note> 
               <hi>and as I have been truly taught in the dayes of that good King</hi> Edward, <hi>of ſuch godly Preachers and Prophets ſent of God, as have ſealed their Doctrine with their Blood; from whom I will diſſent in no point: for I am a poor man without learning, but am commanded
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:180526:37"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:180526:37"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:180526:38"/> of God to follow the counſel of his conſtant Preachers, and ſo do I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to do, God giving me grace and aſſiſtance thereto. As for you, I know you to be none of Chriſts Shepherds, but ravening Wolves, which come to kill and ſcatter the Flock of Chriſt, as the Lord ſaid you ſhould; and do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h will us to beware of you and your poiſoned Doctrine, bidding us to judge you according to your fruits, whereby all men may ſee and know what you be,</hi>
               <note place="margin">We are bound to follow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur true Preachers.</note> 
               <hi>that will not be wilfully blinde. But the good Shepherds have given their lives for the defence of Chriſts Flock; and I am commanded to follow their faithful and godly example, and to confeſs with them one Truth, even to the fire, if God ſhall ſee it good: and this as a true Chriſtian I have hitherto done, and henceforth by Gods grace intend for to do. And if for the ſame, God ſhall ſuffer you to take away my life, as you have done theirs, I am contented therewith: His will be done,</hi>
               <note place="margin">God wil require accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of blood.</note> 
               <hi>for that onely is good. But of this be you ſure, the Lord will ſhortly call you to account for all the innocent blood that is ſhed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this Realm; which you have brought into a moſt woful caſe, and made many a heavy heart in the ſame, and moe I perceive you will make, ſo long as the Lord for our ſins will ſuffer you to prosper, and untill the time that your own iniquity be full ripe. But then be you ſure the Lord will ſit in Judgement upon you, as well as you do now upon his Saints, and will reward you according to your deſervings: To whom with my whole heart I commit my cauſe, and he will make anſwer for me, when the full time of my refreſhing cometh. In the mean space I will keep ſilence with this that I have ſaid, truſting that I have ſufficiently diſcharged my conſcience in confeſſing my Faith and Religion to you, declaring of what Church I am, even of the Catholick Church of Jeſus Chriſt, which was well known to be here in</hi> England <hi>in our late good Kings dayes, by two special to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens which cannot deceive me, nor ſuffer me to be deceived; that is to ſay, The pure Preaching of his holy Word, and the due adminiſtration of the holy Sacraments, which is not to be ſeen in your Romiſh Church, and therefore cannot be called the Church and Spouſe of Chriſt. I believe in the holy Trinity, and all the other Articles of the Chriſtian Faith con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the three Creeds, and finally all the Canonicall Scripture to be true in every ſentence: and I deteſt all Sects both of Arrians and Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts, or any other that divide themſelves from the true Church of Chriſt, which is his Myſticall Body, the Ground and Pillar of Truth,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:180526:38"/> and the very Houſe of the living God. And if for theſe things you take away my life, and make your ſelves guilty of my Blood, you may: for I am in your hands, as the Sheep brought to the Shambles, abiding the grace of the Butcher. And be you ſure, your judgement ſleepeth not, but when you cry Peace, peace, and all is ſafe, then ſhall your plagues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin like the ſorrows of a woman travelling with childe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.</note> 
               <hi>according to Chriſts infallible Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>miſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This kinde of anſwer, my dear heart, it ſhall be beſt for you to make, and by Gods grace I do intend to take the ſame order my ſelf in time to come, when the Lord ſhall vouch me worthy of that great dignity, whereunto he hath called you. And if they ſhall laugh you to ſcorn, as I know they will, ſaying thou art a Fool, and an unlearned Aſs-head, and art able to make anſwer to nothing. &amp;c. care not you for it, but ſtill commit your Cauſe unto God, who will make anſwer for you; &amp; tell them that they have bin anſwered again and again of divers godly and learned men: but all will not help, for you have one ſolution for all manner of que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, even a fair Fire and Fagots: this will be the end of your diſputations. Therefore I pray you to trouble me no more, but do that which you are appointed, when God ſhall permit the time. I am no better then Chriſt, his Apoſtles, and other of my good Brethren that are gone before me.</p>
            <p>This kinde of anſwer will cut their combs moſt, and edifie the people that ſtand by, ſo that the ſame be done coldly with ſobrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, meekneſs and patience; as I heard ſay our ſweet Brethren <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Harland</hi> and <hi>John Oſwald</hi> did at <hi>Lewes</hi> in <hi>Suſſex,</hi> to the great rejoycing of the children of God that were in thoſe parts: and I heard ſay, that they were diſſolved from this earthly tabernacle at <hi>Lewes</hi> on Saturday laſt, and were condemned but the Wedneſday before: ſo that we may perceive the Papiſts have quick work in hand,<note place="margin">2 Chron. 2.</note> that they make ſuch haſte to have us home to our heavenly Father. Therefore let us make our ſelves ready to ride in the fiery Chariot, leaving theſe ſorry Mantles and old Clokes behinde us for a little time, which God ſhall reſtore unto us again in a more glorious wiſe.</p>
            <p>My good Brother <hi>Harry,</hi> you ſhall underſtand that bragging
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:180526:39"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:180526:39"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:180526:40"/> 
               <hi>John T.</hi> hath beguiled his Keepers (who truſted him too well) and is run away from them, and hath brought the poor men into great danger by the ſame. The one of them is caſt by the Councils Commandment into the Gate-houſe at <hi>Weſtminſter;</hi> the other is fled forth of the Country for fear. Thus you may ſee the fruits of our Free-will men, that made ſo much boaſt of their own ſtrength. But that houſe which is not builded ſurely upon the unmoveable Rock, will not long ſtand againſt the boiſterous winds and ſtorms, that blow ſo ſtrongly in theſe dayes of Trouble.</p>
            <p>But my dearly beloved Brother, bleſſed be God for you, and ſuch as you be, which have played the parts of wiſe Builders. You have digged down paſt the ſand of your own natural ſtrength, and beneath the earth of your own worldly wiſdome, and are now come to the hard Stone and unmoveable Rock Chriſt, who is your onely Keeper; and upon him alone you have builded your Faith moſt firmly, without doubting miſtruſt or wavering There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore neither the ſtorms nor tempeſts, winds nor weathers that Satan and all his wily workmen can bring againſt you, with the very Gates of Hell to help them, ſhall ever be able once to move your Houſe, much leſs to overthrow it: for the Lord God himſelf, and no man, is the Builder thereof, and hath promiſed to preſerve and keep the ſame ſafe for ever. Unto his moſt merciful defence therefore, I do heartily commit you and all your good company, deſiring him for his ſweet Son Jeſus Chriſts ſake, to confirm and ſtrengthen you all, that you may be conſtant unto the very end; that after the final victory is once gotten, you may receive the immerceſſible Crown of Glory, of Gods free gift, through his great mercy in Jeſus Chriſt our alone Saviour. To whom with the Father and the Holy Ghoſt, be all honour, glory praiſe, thanks, power, rule and domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, for ever and evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi> The Bleſſing of God be with you all.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Careles.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:180526:40"/>
            <head>To my moſt dear and faithfull Brother <hi>T. V.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe everlaſting peace of God in Ieſus Chriſt, the continual joy and comfort of his moſt pure holy, and mighty Spirit, with the increaſe of Faith and lively feel ng of his mercy, be with you my dear heart in the Lord, and faithful lov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng brother <hi>T. V.</hi> to the full accompliſhing of that good work wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ath ſo graciouſly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun in you, that the ſame, by all means may be to the ſetting forth of his glory, to the commodity of his poor afflicted Congregation, and to the ſweet comfort and quietneſs of your Conſcience in him now and evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With ſuch due honour, love and reverence as it becometh me to bear unto the ſweet Saints, &amp; dearly beloved children of God I have me moſt heartily commended unto you, my dear Brother <hi>V.</hi> with all earneſt and faithfull remembrance of you in my daily Prayers, thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God right heartily that you do likewiſe remember me in yours, aſſuring you that my poor heart doth daily feel great Conſolation thereby, God onely have the praiſe for the ſame, and all other his Benefits. Ah my dear heart in the Lord, well is me that ever I was born, that God of his great mercy and infinite goodneſs hath uſed me moſt miſerable wretch at any time, as his inſtrument, to miniſter any thing unto you, either by word or writing, that might be an occaſion of your joy and comfort in the Lord, and a provoking of you to praiſe and thankſgiv ng unto God for the ſame, as your moſt loving and godly Letter ſeemeth to import. Oh happy am I that the Lord hath appointed me unto ſo good a ground to ſow his ſeed upon; but much more happy are you, whoſe heart the Lord hath prepared and made ſo meet to receive the ſame ſo effectuouſly, g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ving thereto the ſweet ſhowers and heavenly dews of his grace and holy Spirit, that it may bring forth fruit in due ſeaſon ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly; the increaſe whereof we ſhall ſhortly reap together, with perfect joy and gladneſs, and that continually.</p>
            <p>Therefore (my dear Brother) I ſay unto you, as good <hi>Elizabeth</hi> did to her Couſin <hi>Mary, Happy are you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 1.</note> 
               <hi>and happy ſhall you be for evermore, becauſe you have believed.</hi> The moſt ſweet and faithful
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:180526:41"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:180526:41"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:180526:42"/> Promiſes of your Redeemer Jeſus Chriſt, you have ſurely laid up in the treaſury of your heart: his comfortable Callings you have faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully heard: his loving Admonitions you have humbly obeyed, and therefore you ſhall never come into judgement:<note place="margin">Remiſſion of ſins</note> your ſins ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll never be remembred, for your Saviour hath caſt them all into he bottom of the Sea:<note place="margin">Micah 7.</note> he hath removed them from you as far as the Eaſt is from the Weſt,<note place="margin">Pſal. 103.</note> and hath given you for an everlaſting poſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion his Juſtification and Holineſs: So that now no Creature, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in heaven nor in earth, ſhall be able to accuſe you before the Throne of the heavenly King. Satan is now judged: he is now caſt out from you, he hath no part in you: you are wholly given unto Chriſt, which will not loſe you: your ſtedfaſt Faith in him hath overcome that ſturdy and bragging Prince of the World. Chriſt hath given you the final victory over him and all his Army, that they ſhall never hurt you. What would you have more? Oh my dear heart, how great treaſures are laid up in ſtore for you, and how glorious a Crown is already made and prepared for you?</p>
            <p>And albeit the holy Ghoſt doth bear witneſs of all theſe things in your heart,<note place="margin">Teſtimony of Gods Spirit.</note> and maketh you more ſure and certain thereof, then if you had all the outward Oracles in the world; yet I being cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly perſwaded, and fully aſſured by the teſtimony of Gods Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in my Conſcience, of your eternal and ſure Salvation in our ſweet Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, have thought it good yea and my bounden duty, not onely at this time to write unto you, and to ſhew my joyful heart in that behalf; but alſo by the Word and Commandment of Chriſt, to pronounce and affirm in the Name and Word of the heavenly King Jehovah, and in the behalf of his ſweet Son Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, to whom all knees ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll bow, whom all creatures ſhall worſhip, and alſo by the impulſion of the holy Ghoſt by whoſe power and ſtrength all the faithful be regenerate: I do I ſay p onounce to thee my dear B o her <hi>T. V.</hi> that thou art already a Cit zen of Heaven. The Lord thy God, in whom thou doſt put all thy truſt, for his dear Sons ſake, in whom thou doſt alſo undoubtedly believe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a h freely forgiven thee all thy ſins, clearly releaſed all thine in qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ties, and fully pardoned all thine offences, be they never ſo many, ſo grievous, or ſo great, and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:180526:42"/> will never remember them any more to Condemnation. As truly as he liveth, he will not have thee dye the death, but hath verily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined, purpoſed, and eternally decreed, that thou ſhalt live with him for ever. Thy Sore ſhall be healed, and thy Wounds bound up even of himſelf for his own Names ſake. He doth not, nor will not look upon thy ſins in thee, but he reſpecteth and beholdeth thee in Chriſt, in whom thou art lively graffed by Faith in his blood, and in whom thou art moſt aſſuredly elected and choſen to be a ſweet veſſel of his Mercy and Salvation, and waſt thereto pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinate in him before the foundation of the world was laid. In teſtimony and earneſt whereof, he hath given thee his good and holy Spirit, which worketh in thee Faith, Love, and unfeigned Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, with other godly Vertues, contrary to the Corruption of thy Nature.</p>
            <p>Alſo he hath commanded me this day (although a moſt unworthy wretch) to be a witneſs hereof by the Miniſtry of his holy Word,<note place="margin">Experience of Chriſt working in his Church.</note> grounded upon the truth of his moſt faithful Promiſes, the which thou believing, ſhalt live for ever. Believeſt thou this, my dear heart? I know well thou doſt believe. The Lord increaſe thy Faith, and give thee a lively feeling of all his mercies, whereof thou art war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted and aſſured by the teſtimony of the holy Ghoſt, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm in thy Conſcience (to the utter overthrowing of Satan, and thoſe his moſt hurtful dubitations, whereby he is accuſtomed to moleſt and vex the true Children of God) all that I have ſaid: and by Gods grace I will, as a witneſs thereof, confirm and ſeal the ſame with my blood, for a moſt certain truth.</p>
            <p>Wherefore (my good Brother) praiſe the Lord with a joyful heart, and give him thanks for this his exceeding great mercy, caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away all dubitation and wavering, yea all ſorrow of heart and penſiveneſs of mind; for this the Lord your God, and moſt dear and loving Father, commandeth you to do by me, nay rather by his own Mouth and Word pronounced by me. But now my dear Brother, after that I have done my meſſage, or rather the Lords meſſage indeed, I could finde in my heart to write two or three ſheets of paper, declaring the joy I bear in my heart for you, mine own bowels in the Lord: yet the time being ſo ſhort (as you do well know) I
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:180526:43"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:180526:43"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:180526:44"/> am here conſtrained to make an end, deſiring you to pardon my ſlackneſs, and to forgive my great negligence towards you, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing you ſtill, that ſo long as my poor life doth laſt, my prayer ſhall ſupply that my pen doth want; as knoweth the Almighty God, to whoſe moſt merciful defence I do heartily commit you, and all other his dear children, as well as though I had rehearſed them by Name, deſiring them moſt heartily to remember me in their hearty and daily Prayers as I know right well they do: for I feel the daily comfort and commodity thereof and therefore I neither will nor can forget them nor you, or any ſuch like. The bleſſing of God be with you all. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours for ever unfeignedly, <hi>John Careles.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A Letter of Thanks to a faithfull Friend of his, by whom he had received much comfort in his inward troubles.</head>
            <p>BLeſſed be God the Father of all mercy, for the great comfort and Chriſtian conſolation which he hath ſo mercifully miniſtred unto my poor affl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cted heart by your means, my moſt dear and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Brother. Truly me thinketh your words, or rather Gods words by you uttered, have a wonderful power and efficacy working in my heart at the hearing or reading of them. Rejoyce therefore, my dear Brother, and be thankful unto God, for verily he both is and will be mightily magnified in you, and that divers and many wayes, both to the ſtrengthning of them that ſtand in his Truth, and alſo to the raiſing up of ſuch as are faln from the ſame. God make me thankful for you, and on your behalf, for verily great is the goodneſs of God towards me, in giving me acquaintance in faithful love and amity with you: Gods Name for ever be prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed therefore, and he perform all his merciful Promiſes upon you, as I doubt not but he will, for his ſake in whom you truſt.</p>
            <p>I thank my God moſt heartily, and alſo you my good Brother, for that you are careful for me in your faithful Prayers, remembring my juſt deſerved ſorrows, as though they were your own, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:180526:44"/> ſo much to ſolace the ſame. Ah my gracious good God, what am I, for whom thou and thy dear Children ſhould be ſo careful? Oh ſweet Lord, forgive me my great ingratitude and ſin, and grant that I never abuſe thy great benefits. Oh let the love of thine Elect, which love me for thy ſake, be a ſure ſign and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, yea a moſt firm teſtimony and a ſeal to my ſinful Conſcience, of thine everlaſting love and mercy towards me in Chriſt; as verily it would and ought to be, if mine infidelity did not let it. Oh cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſe therefore the fore-skin of my heart, that I may with live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Faith behold thy great love towards me in all thine Elect, that I may alwayes be thankful for the ſame, and love thee and them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain moſt heartily and unfeignedly.</p>
            <p>Ah my dear heart, how ſweetly and how truly, yea how godly and how comfortably have yov rehearſed the ſweet ſaying of <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> concerning proſperity with true and godly friends?<note place="margin">What a treaſure a truſty friend is</note> I will joyn with it the Sentence which goeth a little before, for doubtleſs it may be well verified on you: <hi>A ſure friend</hi> (ſaith the Wiſe-man) <hi>will be unto thee even as thine own Soul, and deal faithfully with thy houſhold folk. If thou ſuffer trouble and adverſity, he is with thee, and hideth not his face from thee. A faithfull friend is a ſtrong defence, whoſe findeth ſuch an one, findeth a treaſure. A faithfull friend hath no peer, the weight of gold is not to be compared to the goodneſs of his faith. A faithfull friend is a medicine of life, and they that fear the Lord ſhall finde him, &amp;c.</hi> Lo (my dear heart in the Lord) here is a lively image or deſcription of you; for verily ſuch an one have I alwayes found you unto me, not onely ſorrowing for my great ſorrow, but alſo oftentimes making me merry and joyful, with ſuch joyes as the world cannot feel.<note place="margin">There is no true friendſhip but amongſt the godly.</note> Now let the world brag of his feigned friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, but I will boaſt of this true friendſhip in God, and eſteem it a more treaſure then all tranſitory things. And as for my mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, dear Brother, God hath made you to turn it unto mirth: for God hath put you in the ſtead of them to be my Comfort, whom he hath in his great mercy taken away. I truſt henceforth to leave the mourning for my great loſs, and to praiſe God for gaining unto himſelf ſo great glory by his choſen children. God make me a true mourner of Sion, both for mine own ſin and wickedneſs, and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:180526:45"/> alſo to ſee his honour defaced, that I may be made meet and apt to hear the joyful and comfortable meſſage that your beautiful feet ſhall bring me. God bleſs thee my dear heart, and faithful loving Brother, and increaſe his good gifts of grace in thee, as he hath moſt happily begun, that you may daily more effectually feel, and lively perceive the certainty of Gods grace wherein you ſtand, and firmly to teſtifie the ſame, to the Converſion or Confounding of all gainſayers, and to the comfort and confirmation of all Gods dear children. <hi>Amen.</hi> Farewel mine own ſweet Brother: farewel as mine own heart.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your own in Chriſt, <hi>John Careles.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>Another Letter of <hi>John Careles</hi> to a certain godly faithful Siſter, by the Name of <hi>E. K.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe grace and free mercy of God in Jeſus Chriſt, the ſweet Conſolations of the holy Ghoſt the guide of all Gods dear Children, be with you, ſtrengthen and comfort you, my dearly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved ſweet Siſter, <hi>E. K.</hi> now and ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Albeit, my dearly beloved Siſter in Chriſt, that as yet we did never ſee one another perſonally to any knowledge, yet by the virtuous report that I have heard of you, and alſo by the large loving Token that I have received from you, methink that I do even preſently ſee you, and behold your perſon, faithfully walking in the fear and love of God, joying and rejoycing with you in the Spirit, as though we were ſweetly talking together of Chriſts Verity. The Lord God do I humbly beſeech in the bowels and blood of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, that he will ſtrengthen us both with his holy and mighty Spirit, that we may conſtantly continue in the confeſſion of his Truth unto the end: that like as we now ſee one another preſently in Spirit, we may alſo ſee one another perſonally in the glorious preſence of God and his holy Angels, where undoubtedly we ſhall know one anothers perſonage, to our great joy, felicity and endleſs Comfort.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Preparation to the Croſs.</note>And now therefore, dear Siſter <hi>K.</hi> be ſtrong in the Lord our
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:180526:45"/> God, for doubtleſs the time of triall is at hand; a great perſecution, with cruel Murthering of Gods dear Saints, is like to be very ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this woful wicked Realm of <hi>England.</hi> Therefore dear Siſter, for the love of God prepare you to the Croſs with all diligence, and make your ſelf ready to dye with Chriſt, that you may alſo live with him for ever. There is no remedy, if you will be Chriſts diſciple, you muſt needs take up your Croſs and follow him, for the Diſciple muſt not look to be above his Maſter, nor the Servant to be better intreated then his Lord. If we were of the World (good Siſter) no doubt the world would love us: But foraſmuch as Chriſt hath choſen us out of the world, to ſerve God in Spirit &amp; Verity, let us be well aſſured the World will hate us and perſecute us, as it hath done our Lord and Maſter Chriſt. But yet let us be of good chear, for Chriſt hath overcome the World. The pain is but ſhort that we can feel here, but the pleaſure is perpetual that we ſhall feel elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where.</p>
            <p>Let us ſet before us the Example of Chriſt, which abode the Croſs, and deſpiſed the ſhame,<note place="margin">Conſolation un<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der the Croſs.</note> in reſpect of the joy that was ſet before him: even ſo let us conſider for whoſe ſake we ſuffer, whoſe Cauſe we defend, and what glorious Reward we ſhall have at the day of our victory, and then doubtleſs the conſolation of theſe things will make ſweet all our ſufferings, and ſoon ſwallow up all the ſorrows that we are ſowled in for Gods ſake. I could recite divers Texts of the Scriptures to confirm this point: but I need not, for I am well aſſured that you do know them moſt perfectly already. The Lord give you ſtrength, and aſſiſt you with his holy Spirit, that you may continually walk in all points according to your godly knowledge: And then ſhall you do not as the moſt part of your Goſpellers do now adayes the more is the pity. There are a great many in <hi>England</hi> that do perfectly know, that the Idolatrous Maſs is abominable, devilliſh, and deteſtable in the ſight of God; and yet, alas they be not afraid to pollute and defile their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, which ought to be the Temples of the holy Ghoſt, with being preſent at it, ſo ſinning againſt God and their own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</p>
            <p>But dear Siſter <hi>K.</hi> do you fly from it both in body and Soul, as
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:180526:46"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:180526:46"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:180526:47"/> you would fly from the very Devil himſelf; Drink not of the Whore of Babylons Cup by no means, for it will infect the Body, and poiſon the Soul. Be not partakers of her ſins (ſaith the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel) leſt you be partakers of the Plagues that ſhortly ſhall be pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red upon her. O what an array is this? that ſo many that know Gods Truth, will now turn again and defile themſelves in the filthy Puddle of Antichriſts ſtinking Religion! They go about to ſave their lives with their double diſſimulation; but doubtleſs they ſhall loſe everlaſting life by it, if they do not Repent in time, and turn unto the Lord. But dear ſiſter, my truſt is that you do utterly ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre the coming to any ſuch thing. I hope that you will not by any means turn back into Egypt now, but that you will boldly venture through the Wilderneſs of Trouble and Perſecution, that you may come into the Land that floweth with all kinde of Heavenly pleaſures and joyful delectations, and poſſeſs the ſame for ever.</p>
            <p>Let us conſider, how that every one of us doth owe unto God a death by nature, and how ſoon the Lord will require it of us, we know not. Oh how happy are we then, if God of his goodneſs appoint us to pay Natures debt with ſuffering for his Truth and Goſpel ſake, and ſo making us his faithful Witneſſes with the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Apoſtles, Martyrs</hi> and <hi>Confeſſors,</hi> yea with his dearly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Son Jeſus Chriſt, to whom he doth here begin to faſhion us like in ſuffering, that we might be like him alſo in glory.</p>
            <p>Thus, my dearly beloved Siſter, I have been bold to trouble you a little with my rude and ſimple Letter, being made in haſte as it doth appear. Yet I deſire you to take it in good worth, as a token of my poor zeal unto you, and do accept my good will: And if it pleaſe God to ſpare me life and liberty, I truſt hereafter to write unto you more largely. Fare ye well dear Siſter <hi>E. K.</hi> the Lord bleſs you and all yours, and pour upon you the heavenly dew of his Grace. The Lord indue you with plentiful knowledge of his Verity, and fill you with his holy and mighty Spirit, that you may continually rejoyce in the Comforts of the ſame now and ever. <hi>Amen.</hi> Pray, pray, pray with ſtedfaſt Faith.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your daily Oratour, <hi>John Careles,</hi> Priſoner of the Lord.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:180526:47"/>
            <head>A Letter of <hi>John Careles</hi> to Mrs. <hi>Agnes Glaſcock.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe everlaſting peace of God in Jeſus Chriſt, the continuall ayd, ſtrength and comforts of his moſt pure, holy and mighty Spirit, be with you my dear and faithfull Siſter <hi>Glaſcock,</hi> to the good performance of that good work which God hath ſo graciouſly begun in you, to his glory, and the commodity of his poor afflicted Church, and to your own eternal comfort in him. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In our Lord I have moſt humble and hearty commendations unto you, my dear Siſter, and moſt faithful Mother <hi>Glaſcock,</hi> with all remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of you in my daily Prayers, giving God moſt hearty land, praiſe and thanks for you, and on your behalf, in that he of his great mercy hath hitherto ſo mightily ſtrengthned you, conſtantly to cleave unto your Captain Chriſt, notwithſtanding the great aſſaults and manifold tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that you have had to the contrary. Doubtleſs, dear heart, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be expreſſed what joy and comfort it is unto my very Soul, to ſee how mightily the Lord hath magnified himſelf in you, and other his dear elect darlings, whom he will ſhortly glorifie with himſelf, as he hath done other of his ſweet Saints that are gone before you. Rejoyce therefore and be glad, for verily you have good cauſe, if you diligently conſider the great dignity that God hath called you unto even in your old age, to be one of his worthy Witneſſes unto the World, and I think you ſhall with me and other your Brethren in Bonds, ſeal the Lords Verity with the Teſtimony of your Blood. Surely, ſweet Siſter,<note place="margin">What an high honour it is to ſuffer for Chriſt.</note> this is the greateſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion that God can bring you or any other unto in this life, and an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour that the higheſt Angel in Heaven is not permitted to have.</p>
            <p>Therefore happy are you, Oh faithful daughter of <hi>Abraham,</hi> that the Lord will now preferre you before many other, yea or any other of your age, that I do know in <hi>England.</hi> Oh faithful and virtuous Matron, which wilt not be moved from the ſure Rock Chriſt, upon whom you have ſo firmly built your houſe, that neither ſtorms nor tempeſts, neither yet Hell gates, or any other temptations, ſhall ever be able once to prevail againſt it. Full well doth it appear by your conſtant continuance, that you have played the part of a wiſe builder, in counting the Coſt afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand belonging to the finiſhing of your Tower, and I doubt not but
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:180526:48"/> (through Gods gift) you have ſufficient to the performance thereof, that the Hypocrites of their part ſhall have no juſt cauſe to triumph againſt you, or to mock you, ſaying, Lo, this woman began to build, but is not able to make an end. Therefore go on boldly, and fear not; for God is faithfull (as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith) which will not ſuffer you to be tempted above your ſtrength, but either will he give you grace and ſtrength to ſtand unto the death, (which is the gate and entrance into life) or elſe he will make ſuch an out-ſcape for you, as ſhall be to the ſetting forth of his glory; the which above all other things, we that are his choſen chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ought for to ſeek, yea even with the loſs of our own lives, being yet well aſſured that the ſame ſhall not be ſhortned one minute of an hour before the time that God hath appointed.</p>
            <p>Caſt therefore (dear Siſter) all your care upon the Lord, which (as S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith) careth for you. Great is his Providence for you, and mighty is his love and mercy towards you: with his grace he will defend you, and with his holy Spirit he will evermore guide you, wherewith he hath ſurely ſealed you unto the day of Redemption: He hath alſo given you the ſame in earneſt for the recovery of the purchaſed Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which he hath prepared for you before the foundation of the world was laid. Be ſtrong therefore, and take a good heart, as I hear ſay you be. God for ever be bleſſed for you, which hath graft his love in your good heart, that nothing is able to ſeparate you from the ſame, but will rather chuſe to ſuffer adverſity with the people of God, then to enjoy the pleaſures of ſin for a little ſeaſon. Oh happy woman, that canſt finde in thine heart to eſteem the rebukes of Chriſt to be greater riches then all the treaſures of the world, as good <hi>Moſes</hi> did. Doubtleſs great is your reward in Heaven, which you ſhall ſhortly receive of his free gift, and not of any deſerving.</p>
            <p>Thus dear Mother <hi>Glaſcock,</hi> I have been bold to trouble you with my rude and ſimple Letters, deſiring you to take them in good worth, being done in great haſte, as it doth appear; but yet proceeding from a poor heart, which floweth over in love towards you, as my daily prayers for you can teſtifie, which I truſt ſhall ſupply that part of my duty to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you, that my Pen now wanteth. I thank you, dear heart, for all your loving Tokens, and for the great kindneſs you have hitherto ſhewed unto my poor Brother <hi>Tyms,</hi> and his Wife and Children, with
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:180526:48"/> all other of Gods people to whom you daily do good: the Lord recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence the ſame ſevenfold into your boſome, as I doubt not but he will, according to his infallible Promiſes. I pray you have my hearty com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations unto your Husband. I beſeech the Lord ſtrengthen him in the Confeſſion of his Truth (as my truſt is that he will) that we may all joyfully reſt with <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> in the Kingdome of God; unto the which he bring us, that with his moſt precious blood hath bought us. The Bleſſing of God be with you now and ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your daily Orator and unfeigned Lover, <hi>John Careles,</hi> Priſoner of the Lord, <hi>Pray, pray, pray.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A brief Admonition written by <hi>John Careles</hi> to Mrs. <hi>Agnes Glaſcock,</hi> in a Book of hers when ſhe came to the Priſon to viſit him.</head>
            <p>THere is nothing that the holy Scripture throughout doth ſo much commend unto us, as true Faith, and ſtedfaſt truſt in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of Gods eternal mercies towards us in Jeſus Chriſt. For from the ſame, as forth of the chief Fountain and Well-spring of life, do flow all kindes of virtues and godly fruits, specially true love towards God, in the which we ought purely to ſerve him all the dayes of our life: and alſo Chriſtian Charity towards our Neighbours, as well to help them at all needs, as alſo not to hurt them by any means. Therefore pray ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly for the increaſe of faith, and lively feeling of Gods mercy: for all things are poſſible to him that can undoubtedly believe.<note place="margin">The effects of Faith.</note> Faith is that thing which aſſureth us of Gods mercy, and whereby we vanquiſh all the fiery darts of the Devil: Our victory that overcometh the world: The knife that killeth and mortifieth the fleſh: and finally, that which ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth us at peace with God, and quieteth our Conſciences alwayes before him, and maketh us merry and joyfull under the Croſs, with many moe things then I can now expreſs. Pray therefore for faith, in faith. And for the Lords ſake, beware of Popery, and Popiſh Idolatry, the Idol of the wicked Maſs, and other Idolatrous Service. Make not
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:180526:49"/> your body, which is a member of Chriſt, a member of Antichriſt. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that we ſhall receive of God according to that we do in the body, be it good or evil. Therefore glorifie God in your body, which is dearly bought. Betray not the Truth, leſt the Lord deny you. If God be God, follow him. You cannot ſerve two Maſters. I write not this as doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you, but by the way of Admonition. God keep you from all evil.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>My Siſter dear, God give you grace</l>
               <l>With ſtedfaſt Faith in Chriſt his Name,</l>
               <l>His Gospel ſtill for to embrace,</l>
               <l>And live according to the ſame.</l>
               <l>To dye therefore, think it no ſhame,</l>
               <l>But hope in God with faithfull truſt:</l>
               <l>And he will give you praiſe with fame,</l>
               <l>When you ſhall riſe out of the duſt.</l>
               <l>For which moſt ſweet and joyfull day,</l>
               <l>To God with faith your Prayer make;</l>
               <l>And think on me I do you pray,</l>
               <l>The which did write this for your ſake.</l>
               <l>And thus to God I you betake,</l>
               <l>Who is your Caſtle and ſtrong Rock:</l>
               <l>He keep you whether you ſleep or wake.</l>
               <l>Farewell dear Miſtris <hi>A. Glaſcock.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>An other Letter of <hi>John Careles</hi> to Mrs. <hi>A. G.</hi> to comfort her in her repentance, after ſhe had been at Maſs, fruitful for all them to be read, which have fallen, and are to be raiſed up again.</head>
            <p>THe peace of God in Jeſus Chriſt, the eternal comforts of his ſweet Spirit be with you, and ſtrengthen and comfort you my dear and fait<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ful Siſter. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Although the perillous dayes be come, whereof Chriſt prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied, that if it were poſſible the very elect ſhould be deceived; yet let the true faithful Chriſtians rejoyce and be glad, knowing that the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:180526:49"/> Lord himſelf is their keeper, who will not ſuffer one hair of their heads to periſh without his almighty good will and pleaſure, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will ſuffer them to be further tempte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> then he will give them ſtrength to bear: but will in the midſt of their temptations make a way for them to eſcape out. So good and gracious a God is he to all his choſen Children. And though ſometimes he do let his elect ſtumble and fall, yet (no doubt) he will raiſe them up again to the further increaſe of their comfort, and to the ſetting forth of his glory and praiſe. Which thing (my dear and faithful loving Siſter) I truſt ſhall be well verified on you: for I do hear ſay that by the manifold allurements, inticements, procurements, yea and inforcements that you dear heart have had, your foot hath chanced to ſlip forth of the way, to the great diſcomfort of your Soul, and the heavineſs of your heart. But my good Siſter, be of good chear, for the Lord will not ſo leave you, but he will raiſe you up again, and make you ſtronger then ever you were; ſo that your fall ſhall turn to his glory &amp; your profit. For if you had not by this proved the experience of your own ſtrength, or rather your own weakneſs, you would have ſtood too much in your own Conceit, or perchance have gloried in your ſelf, and have deſpiſed and condemned other weak perſons that have committed the like offence. Therefore now you may ſee what the beſt of us all can do, if God leave us to our ſelves. Which thing ought to move you to be diligent to call earneſtly upon God for his grace, and the ſtrength of his Holy Spirit (without the which we are not able to ſtand one hour) and to be moſt thankful for the ſame when you have it, and then to be more circumſpect in time to come.</p>
            <p>Therefore dear Siſter, ſeeing that you have done otherwiſe then the word of God and your own Conſcience would allow, yet dear heart, do you not think that God therefore will caſt you clean away; but know, that he hath mercy enough in ſtore for all them that truly repent and believe in him, although the ſins of them were as many in number as the ſands in the Sea, and as great as the ſins of the whole world. It is a greater ſin to miſtruſt the mercy &amp; promiſes of God, then to commit the greateſt offence in the World. Therefore, (good Siſter) beware in any wiſe,<note place="margin">To truſt to Gods Promiſes.</note> that you do not once miſtruſt
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:180526:50"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:180526:50"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:180526:51"/> the promiſes of Gods mercy towards you; but know for a very ſurety, that all your ſins be utterly forgiven you for Chriſts ſake, be they never ſo many, ſo gri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vous, or ſo great.</p>
            <p>But now (dear heart) take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eed and beware that you do not cloke that ſin, and increaſe the ſame daily, in communicating with the wicked in their Idolatry, and deviliſh doings at their den of Thieves.<note place="margin">Cuſtome of ſin a perilous matter.</note> Do not (I ſay) dear Siſter, come at any of their Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian ſervice, leſt by little and little you utterly loſe a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and at length eſteem it for none offence; as (alas) a great number doth at this day, to the great peril of their Souls. The Lord be merciful unto them, and give them grace to repent in time, and turn to the Lord, and then they ſhall be ſure to finde mercy at the Lords hand, as doubtleſs you have done, praiſed be his Name therefore.</p>
            <p>Ah my dear Siſter, you may now ſee the words of Chriſt verified up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your ſelf, that a mans greateſt foes ſhall be they of his own houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>A. G.</hi> entiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d by her huſband to go to the Maſs.</note> for your Husband hath gotten you to do that, which all the tyrants in the World could never have made you to do. Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he may be ſorry for it: God give him grace to repent, or elſe, without doubt, it will be laid to his charge one day, when he would not by his will hear it for all the goods of the World. Well, I think my Brother <hi>Tyms</hi> will write him a letter ſhortly that ſhall touch his Conſcience, if he have any Conſcience at all.</p>
            <p>But now again to you dear Siſter. The thing that is done cannot be undone, and you are not the firſt that have offended, neither are you ſo good and ſo holy, as hath at a time ſlipt forth of the way. Therefore I would not have you to be ſo much diſcomforted as I hear ſay you be,<note place="margin">The raiſing up of a troubled Conſcience after his fall.</note> as though God were not as able to forgive you your offence as he was to forgive his dear Saints that offended him in times paſt; or as though God were not as merciful now as ever he was: whereas in very deed, there is with the Lord as the Prophet ſaith) mercy and plentiful redemption; and his mercy farre ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounteth all his works;<note place="margin">God turneth all things to the beſt to them that be hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and he never faileth any that put their whole truſt and confidence in him, how great an offender, or how wicked a treſpaſſer ſoever he be. No, he maketh their falls and backſlidings many times to turn to their profit and commodity, and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:180526:51"/> to the ſetting forth of his glory: as doubtleſs dear Siſter, yours ſhall do, if you put your whole Faith, hope, and truſt onely in his infinite and eternal ſweet mercies.</p>
            <p>Oh what a ſubtile, crafty, lying Serpent is that Satan our old Enemy,<note place="margin">Satan when he cannot bring a man to his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o, he preſſeth him w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt of Gods mercy.</note> that when he ſeeth that he cannot make us to continue in our wickedneſs to do him ſervice, would then bring us into a doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and miſtruſting of the mercy of God, which is the greateſt offence that can be; yea, infidelity is the root and original of all other ſins. Therefore (my ſweet Siſter) give no place to that cruel adverſary of mankinde, who hath been a lyer and a mutherer from the beginning, but ſtedfaſtly believe the Lord, who hath ſent you word by me his moſt unworthy Servant, that all your ſins be pardoned, forgiven, and clean releaſed for Jeſus Chriſts ſake our onely Lord and Saviour. To whom with the Father, and the holy Ghoſt, be all honour, glory, praiſe, thanks, power, rule, and dominion for ever and for ever. <hi>Amen.</hi> Farewel my dear Siſter, and be of good chear. Believe in the Lord and you ſhall live for ever. The Lord increaſe your Faith. <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your poor Brother and daily faithful Orator, <hi>John Careles,</hi> Priſoner of the Lord. Pray for me.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>Another Letter of <hi>John Careles</hi> to <hi>A. B.</hi> a faithfull Miniſter of the Lord, containing certain fruitfull Precepts of Matrimony.</head>
            <p>I Beſeech the ſame everlaſting Lord (my dear and faithful Brother) that bleſſed young <hi>Tobias</hi> with his Wife <hi>Sarah,</hi> and brought them together in due time with reverence and fear, preſerve and bleſs you both, and your ſeed after you, that they may increaſe the number of the faithful by thouſands and thouſands. And as the Lord of his great mercy and fatherly Providence hath been alwayes careful for you, and now hath for your comfort accompliſhed his good work in coupling you with a faithful Mate: ſo ſee that you
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:180526:52"/> be thankful for his Providence towards you, that it may every way in you be an increaſe of love and godlineſs, yea of Chriſtian joy and gladneſs in theſe ſorrowful dayes: but yet ſo, that you mourn with the true mourners of Sion, and be ſorry (yet in meaſure) for the hurt of the ſame. Pray alſo in faith for her pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity, that the Lord may build up the walls of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 146.</note>Oh that the Lord would turn Sions. Captivity as the river, into the South; then ſhould our hearts be made glad, and our mouthes filled with laughter. Then would the Heathen Hypocrites ſay, The Lord hath done much for them. Oh, the Lord hath done great things for us already, whereof let us heartily rejoyce, and praiſe his Name therefore. For though we now ſow with tears, yet ſhall we be ſure to reap with gladneſs: and as we now go forth weeping, bearing forth good ſeed, ſo ſhall we come again with joy,<note place="margin">The death of the Martyrs is the life of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel.</note> and bring our ſheaves full of Corn. Yea, the death of the Martyrs (which is moſt precious in his ſight) ſhall be the life of the Goſpel, ſpight of the Papiſts hearts.</p>
            <p>Pray for me (dear heart) that I may be counted worthy to ſowe ſome ſeed amongſt the ſweet Saints of the Lord, that I may reap the ſame again without ceaſing,<note place="margin">A ſowing time is Chriſts Church.</note> at the Harveſt. It is now ſowing time of the year, men ſay in the Country, and I think I ſhall make an end of ſowing before all March be paſt: for I hear ſay that I ſhall prove how my Plough will enter into the ſtony ground of the hard hearted Papiſts, within theſe four dayes. I hope to hold faſt, and not to look back, neither for fear nor flattery, until I have made an end of ſowing, and then will I ſet me down and reſt me, and ask them all no leave, and look for the lively fruit and increaſe thereof with joy and gladneſs.</p>
            <p>My dear Brother, the time approacheth near (I praiſe God there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) that I muſt put off this ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ful tabernacle and go home to my heavenly Father, where divers of my dear Brethren are already, looking and wiſhing for me. I beſeech you therefore that you will help me forward with your faithful Prayers, as I know you doe, for I do feel the comfort and commodity thereof.</p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:180526:52"/>
            <p>That you have obſerved my ſimple Counſell, I am right glad,<note place="margin">This counſel was that he ſhould marry, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding certain lets, whereby Satan ſought to hinder his Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage.</note> and I truſt in the Lord God, you ſhall finde comfort in the ſame. And that you may ſo doe indeed, I have been ſo bold to write theſe few words unto you, becauſe I ſhall ſee you no more in this corruptible life: therefore mark them well. Firſt and above all things you muſt be very circumſpect to keep the band of love, and beware that there never ſpring up the root of bitterneſs between you. If at any time there happen to riſe any cauſe of unkindneſs between you (as it is unpoſſible alwayes to be free from it) ſee that you weed up the ſame with all lenity, gentleneſs and patience,<note place="margin">The root of bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs to be weeded out with the Spade of Patience.</note> and never ſuffer your ſelf, nor your wife to ſleep in diſpleaſure.</p>
            <p>If you have cauſe to ſpeak ſharply, and ſometimes to reprove,<note place="margin">How and when the husband ought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove.</note> beware that you do not the ſame in the preſence of other: but keep your words until a convenient time (which is the point of a wiſe man, ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) and then utter them in the ſpirit of meekneſs, and the groaning ſpirit of perfect love: which you muſt alſo let ſometimes to cover faults, and wink at them if they be not intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. Whatſoever loſs and miſchance ſhall happen unto you,<note place="margin">Faults ſomtime muſt be covered with love.</note> take it patiently, and bear it merrily: and though the ſame ſhould come partly through your wifes negligence, yet let it rather be a loving warning to take heed in time to come, then a cauſe of ſorrow for that which is paſt and cannot be holpen. I know by mine own experience that we are in this life ſubj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ct to many inconveniences, and that of nature we are prone to diſpleaſure,<note place="margin">Not to take un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindneſs for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very trifle.</note> and ready to think unkindeneſs for every little trifle, and ſpecially with our beſt friends, yea ſooneſt with our loving wives, which be moſt lotheſt to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe us.</p>
            <p>But let us beware of this cankered corruption, and conſider that wrought moſt of all, in love to bear with them, according to Chriſts example towards his Congregation, for whom he gave himſelf to cleanſe it, &amp;c. I had thought to have treated this matter at large, but even now I am interrupted and otherwiſe letted. I doubt not but you know your duty therein a great deal better then I can declare it unto you; and as you know it, ſo will do it: but I love to be bold with you. I intend alſo to write to your wife very ſhortly, and ſo take my laſt farewel of you forever in this World
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:180526:53"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:180526:53"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:180526:54"/> And thus in great haſte I am now conſtrained to make an end. The bleſſing of God be alwayes with you.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your own forever, <hi>John Careles. Pray, pray, pray with Faith.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>Another Letter of <hi>John Careles</hi> to <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> Wife of the ſaid <hi>A. B.</hi> containing likewiſe certain godly Precepts of Matrimony pertaining to her duty.</head>
            <p>THe everlaſting peace of God in Ieſus Chriſt, the continual ayd, ſtrength and comfort of his moſt holy and mighty Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, with increaſe of knowledge, faith, and perfect feeling of Gods eternal mercy, be with you my dear and faithful loving Siſter, <hi>E. B.</hi> and with your godly loving husband, and my dear and faithful Brother, to the full performance of that good which he hath ſo graciouſly begun in you, that in all things you may be mad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> rich and bleſſed in him, and your ſeed after you, now and ever <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As I have been long deſirous to write unto you (my dear heart i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Lord) not onely being thereto bound of duty, but alſo ofte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> provoked of him, to whom I owe my ſelf, and all that I am able to do (I mean, even that bleſſed of the Lords own mouth, whom God hath joyned with you in that holy and Chriſtian ſtate of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony) even ſo at the laſt I have obtained time and occaſion, in ſome part to perform that which I have long purpoſed. And for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as the Lord of his great mercy and fatherly Care and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence over you his dear childe, hath now graciouſly accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that good work among many other, which I (as a friend of the Bridegroom) have full heartily wiſhed, and often prayed for: I think it good, yea and my bounden duty, to treat of ſuch things as may be profitable to preſerve mutual love and faithful amity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween you;<note place="margin">Satan an enemy to all godly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs.</note> which I know Satan will chiefly labour to diminiſh, if he cannot altogether deſtroy the ſame, leſt by many joyful occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions you ſhould be provoked continually to praiſe God for his
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:180526:54"/> good g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ft, which that enemy hath by all means ſought to hinder from you.</p>
            <p>As for all other things, I know you are ſufficiently inſtructed, and alſo have a moſt godly learned Companion, who is well able further to teach you, if need do require. But in this thing I know my Experience is more then his. Therefore, my good Siſter, firſt and before all things, ſee that you do diligently conſider, that as every good and perfect gift pertaining to Soul and Body, is given from above, and cometh from the Father of Light: Even ſo to whomſoever the Lord dealeth any of his benefits, of them he doth chiefly require alwayes a thankful heart for the ſame; for elſe he will either take away his good gifts again, or turn the ſame to their great diſcommodity, and in the end to the increaſe of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation: So deteſtable in his ſight is the Sin of Ingratitude.<note place="margin">The ſin of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude.</note> But to ſuch as be thankful for his benefits, he doth not onely to the old, ever adde new, but alſo maketh the commodity of his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer gifts ever more and more to increaſe, untill by them they are fully perſwaded, and throughly certified of his everlaſting love in Chriſt Jeſus, which is eternal life it ſelf: ſo much doth he of his great mercy delight in a thankful heart.</p>
            <p>Therefore I do yet once again earneſtly require you, that above all things you be thankful to God for his benefits;<note place="margin">God loveth a thankful hoart.</note> not onely for your Election, Creation, Redemption, and Preſervation, but alſo for his other temporal gifts wherewith he hath endued you: amongſt the which, the chief and moſt excellent is (as teſtifieth the holy Ghoſt) your good, godly, and faithful loving Husband. For (as the Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſaith) Goods and poſſeſſions may come to a man by the death of his friends, but a good Wife is the gift of God,<note place="margin">A good wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e gift of Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> which the Lord will give for a good portion to ſuch as fear him.</p>
            <p>And the like is of a good Husband, as the Lord hath now given you, praiſed be his Name therefore. He hath not given you an ignorant, froward, churliſh, brawling, waſtful, rioting, drunken Husband, wherewith he hath plagued many other (as he might alſo have done you) but he hath given you a moſt godly, lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ned, gentle, loving, quiet, patient, thrifty, diligent, and ſober Husband, by whom he will nouriſh, cheriſh, keep and defend you, inſtruct and teach
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:180526:55"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:180526:55"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:180526:56"/> you, yea care and provide for you and your Children (the which he will alſo by him give you) ſuch things as be neceſſary for you. He hath not dealt ſo with every body; and yet he hath done this and much more for you my dear Siſter, and will thereto increaſe joy and love between you:<note place="margin">God delighteth in the agreement between Man &amp; Wife.</note> for as he delighteth in the love &amp; godly agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of man &amp; wife together, ſo is it he only that maketh them and all the whole houſhold to be of one mind. Unto the which his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious work he requireth your diligence, and will uſe you as his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument and mean, the more effectuouſly to accompl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh the ſame. And therefore I now require you to obſerve this my ſimple counſel, the which I have here written as a teſtimonial of my good will towards you, becauſe I think in this life I ſhall never more ſee you.</p>
            <p>Now, as I have ſhewed you how you ſhould be thankful unto God for his good gifts: ſo I exhort you, and (as much as in me lieth) charge you to be evermore thankful unto your dear loving husband who hath given himſelf unto you; which is a more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious jewel in the Church of God, then perchance you are yet aware of.<note place="margin">The duty of Wives toward their Husbands.</note> Think your ſelf unworthy to be matched with ſuch an Inſtrument of God; and alſo reverence evermore the gifts of God in him, and ſeek with true obedience and love to ſerve him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in recompence of his true and painful heart towards you. Be loth in any wiſe to offend him; yea, rather be careful and diligent to pleaſe him, that his Soul may bleſs you. If at any time you ſhall chance to anger him, or to do or ſpeak any thing that ſhall grieve him, ſee that you never reſt until you have pacified him, and made him merry again.</p>
            <p>If at any time he ſhall chance to blame you without a cauſe, or for that you cannnot do therewith (which thing happeneth ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times of the beſt men living) ſee that you bear it patiently, and give him no uncomely or unkinde word for it; but ever more look upon him with a loving and chearful countenance, and rather take the fault upon you, then ſeem to be diſpleaſed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A chearful coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance.</note>Be alwayes merry and chearful in his company, but not with too much lightneſs. Beware in any wiſe of ſwelling, powting, or lowring, for that is a token of a cruel and unloving heart; except
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:180526:56"/> it be in reſpect of ſin, or in the time of ſickneſs.</p>
            <p>Be not ſorrowful for any adverſity that God ſendeth: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware that nothing be ſpilt or go to waſte through your negligence. In any wiſe ſee rhat you be quick and cleanly about his meat and drink, and prepare him the ſame according to his diet in due ſeaſon.<note place="margin">Temperance in apparrel.</note> Go cleanly and well favouredly in your Apparel, but beware of of Pride in any wiſe.</p>
            <p>Finally, in word and deed ſhew your ſelf wiſe, humble, merry, and loving towards him, and alſo towards ſuch as he doth love, and then ſhall you lead a bleſſed life. I could ſpeak of many other things, the which I have learned and proved true by experience: but I know that you will do in all things much better then I can teach you, becauſe you have that anointing that teacheth you all things; who hath alſo given you an heart to obey and ſerve him. Yet I truſt you will not be offended for this which I have written, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther accept my good will towards you, whom I love in the Lord, as well as I do my daughter <hi>Judith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus as mine own Soul, I commend you both to God, deſiring him to bleſs you with all manner of Spiritual bleſſings in heavenly things, and alſo with the dew of Heaven, and fatneſs of the Earth, that in all things you may be made rich in Jeſus Chriſt our Lord and onely Saviour. The Lord increaſe and bleſs the fruit of your bodyes, that your Children may ſtand round about your Table, thick, freſh, and luſty, like the Olive branches. God give you both a long life, that you may ſee and bleſs your Childrens Children, unto the third and fourth Generation, and teach them the true fear and love of God, and that Faith for the which they ſhall be accepted in his ſight.</p>
            <p>God let you ſee the proſperity of Sion; for whoſe lying in the duſt let your hearts mourn. The Lord make perfect your love together in him, and alwayes increaſe the ſame,<note place="margin">Note, that both theſe departed in quiet peace, the one 1565. the other 1568.</note> and bring you both in peace to your graves, at a good age. And now I bid you both moſt heartily farewel: and I think I ſhall now take my leave of you for ever in this life. I beſeech you both to aid me with your continual Prayers (as I will not forget you in mine) that I may have a joyful victory through Jeſus Chriſt: To whoſe moſt merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:180526:57"/> defence, I do moſt heartily for ever commend you to be kept unblameable untill his coming. The which I beſeech him to haſten for his Mercies ſake.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your own unfeignedly, <hi>John Careles,</hi> Priſoner of the Lord.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>
               <hi>Here endeth the Letters of</hi> John Careles.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A Letter of Mr. <hi>John Bradfords,</hi> which he wrote to a faithfull Woman in her heavineſs and trouble: moſt comfortable for all thoſe to reade that are afflicted and broken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted for their ſins.</head>
            <p>GOd our good Father for his mercies ſake in Chriſt, with his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Conſolation ſo comfort you, as I deſire to be comforted of him in my moſt need: yea, he will comfort you, my dear Siſter; onely caſt your care upon him, and he never can nor will forſake you For his calling and gifts be ſuch, that he can never repent him of them.<note place="margin">Rom. 11.</note> Whom he loveth, he loveth to the end: none of his cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen can periſh. Of which number I know you are, my dearly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Siſter: God increaſe the faith thereof daily more and more in you: he give unto you to hang wholly on him and on his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence and Protection.<note place="margin">Gods Providence and Protection.</note> For who ſo dwelleth under that Secret thing, and help of the Lord, he ſhall be cock-ſure for evermore. He that dwelleth,<note place="margin">Pſal. 31.90.</note> I ſay: for if we be flitters, and not dwellers, as was <hi>Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> a flitter from <hi>Segor,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 19.</note> where God promiſed him protection, if he had dwelled there ſtill; we ſhall remove to our loſs, as he did into the Mountains.</p>
            <p>Dwell therefore, that is, truſt, and that finally unto the end, in the Lord my dear Siſter) and you ſhall be as Mount Sion. As Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains compaſs <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ſo doth the Lord all his people. How then can he forget you, which are as the apple of his eye, for his dear Sons ſake. Ah dear heart, that I were now but one half hour with you, to be a <hi>Simon</hi> to help to carry your Croſs with you. God
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:180526:57"/> ſend you ſome good <hi>Simon</hi> to be with you, and help you.</p>
            <p>You complain in your Letters of the blindneſs of your minde; and the troubles you feel. My dearly beloved, God make you thankful for that which he hath given unto you: he open your eyes to ſee what and how great benefits you have received, that you may be leſs covetous, or rather impatient, for ſo (I fear me) it ſhould be called, and more thankful. Have not you received at his hands, ſight to ſee your blindeneſs, and thereto a deſirous and ſeeking heart to ſee where he lyeth in the mid-day, as his dear Spouſe ſpeaketh of her ſelf in the Canticles? Oh <hi>Joyce,</hi> my good <hi>Joyce,</hi> what a gift is this? Many have ſome ſight, but none this ſobbing and ſighing, none this ſeeking which you have I know, but ſuch as he hath mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried unto him in his mercies. You are nor content to kiſs his feet with the <hi>Magdalen,</hi> but you would be k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſed even with the kiſſes of his mouth, <hi>Can<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 1. You would ſee his face, with <hi>Moſes,</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting how he biddeth us ſeek his face, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27. yea, and that for ever, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. which ſignifieth no ſuch ſi ht as you deſire, to be in this preſent life, which would ſee God now face to face,<note place="margin">God cannot be ſe n, but cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed under ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. How faith ſeeth God, where fleſh ſeeth Hell.</note> whereas he cannot be ſeen but covered under ſomething: yea ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time in that which is (as you would ſay) clean contrary to God; as to ſee his Mercy in his Anger. In bringing us to Hell, Faith ſeeth him bring us to Heaven; in darkneſs, it beholdeth brightneſs; in hiding his face from us, it beholdeth his merry countenance. How did Job ſee God, but as you would ſay under Satans cloke? for who caſt the fire from Heaven upon his goods? who overthrew his houſe, and ſtirred up men to take away his Cattel, but Satan? And yet Job pierced through all theſe, and ſaw Gods work, ſaying, <hi>The Lord hath give, he Lord hath taken away, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In reading of the Pſalms, how often do you ſee that <hi>David</hi> in the ſhadow of death, ſaw Gods ſweet love? And ſo (my dearly beloved) I ſee that you in your darkneſs and dimneſs, by Faith to ſee clarity and brightneſs: by Faith (I ſay) becauſe Faith is of things abſent, of things hoped for, of things which I appeal to your Conſcience, whether you deſire not. And can you deſire any thing which you know not? And is there of heavenly things any other true knowledge then by Faith?</p>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:180526:58"/>
            <p>Therefore, my dear heart, be thankful, for (before God I write it) you have great cauſe. Ah my <hi>Joyce,</hi> how happy is the ſtate wherein you are?<note place="margin">The ſtate of Gods Children deſcribed.</note> Verily you are even in the bleſſed ſtate of Gods Children: for they mourn, and do not you ſo? and that not for worldly weal, but for ſpiritual riches, Faith, Hope, Charity, &amp;c. Do you not hunger and thirſt for righteouſneſs? And I pray you, ſaith not Chriſt,<note place="margin">Matth. 5.</note> who cannot lye, that happy are ſuch? How ſhould God wipe away the tears from your eyes in Heaven, if now on earth you ſhed no tears? How could Heaven be a place of reſt, if on Earth you did finde it? How could you deſire to be at home, if in your journey you found no grief? How could you ſo often call upon God, and talk with him, as I know you do, if your enemy ſhould ſleep all day long? How ſhould you elſwhere be made like unto Chriſt, I mean in joy, if in ſorrow you ſobbed not with him? If you will have joy and felicity, you muſt firſt needs feel ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and miſery.<note place="margin">The way to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is to go through hell.</note> If you will go to Heaven, you muſt ſayle by Hell. If you will embrace Chriſt in his robes, you muſt not think ſcorn of him in his rags. If you will ſit at Chriſts Table in his Kingdome, you muſt firſt abide with him in his Temptations. If you will drink of his cup of glory, forſake not his cup of Ignominy.</p>
            <p>Can the head Corner-ſtone be rejected, and the other more baſe ſtone in Gods building be in this World ſet by? you are one of his lively ſtones: be content therefore to be hewn and ſnagged at, that you might be made the more meet to be joyned to your fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows which ſuffer with you Satans ſnatches, the Worlds wounds, contempt of Conſcience,<note place="margin">Frets of the fleſh</note> and frets of the fleſh, where-through they are enforced to cry: Oh wretches that we are, who ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver us?<note place="margin">Rom. 6.</note> You are of Gods Corn, fear not therefore the Flayle, the Fan, Milſtone, nor Oven. You are one of Chriſts Lambs, look therefore to be fleeced, hayled at, and even ſlain.</p>
            <p>If you were a Market ſheep, you ſhould go in more fat and graſſy Paſture.<note place="margin">Gods ſheep muſt feed on the bare Common, where the devils ctatel are ſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>d.</note> If you were for the Fair, you ſhould be ſtalfed, and want no weal: but becauſe you are for Gods own occupying, therefore you muſt paſture on the bare Common, abiding the ſtorms and tempeſts that will fall. Happy, and twice happy are you (my dear Siſter) that God now haileth you whither you would not,<note place="margin">John 21.</note>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:180526:58"/> that you might come whither you would. Suffer a little, and be ſtill. Let Satan rage againſt you, let the World cry out, let your Conſcience accuſe you, let the Law load you and preſs you down; yet ſhall they not prevail for Chriſt is <hi>Emanuel,</hi> that is, <hi>God with us. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God be with us, who can be againſt us?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> The Lord is with you; your Father cannot forget you; your Spouſe loveth you. If the waves and ſurges ariſe, cry with <hi>Peter, Lord I periſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 8.</note> and he will put out his hand and help you. Caſt out your Anchor of Hope, and it will not ceaſe for all the ſtormy ſurges, till it take hold on the Rock of Gods Truth and Mercy.</p>
            <p>Think not that he which hath given you ſo many things corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, as inductions of ſpiritual and heavenly Mercies,<note place="margin">Philip. 1. Deſire of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual comfort, though it be lacking, is a great gift of God</note> and that without your deſerts or deſire, can deny you any ſpiritual com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort deſiring it. For if he give to deſire, he will give you to have and enjoy the thing deſired. To deſire to have, and the going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to ask, ought to certifie your Conſcience, that they be his earneſt of the thing which you asking he will give you, yea before you ask, and whileſt you are about to ask he will grant the ſame (as <hi>Eſay</hi> ſaith) to his glory, and your eternal conſolation. He that ſpared not his own Son for you, will not nor cannot think any thing too good for you, my heartily beloved.</p>
            <p>If he had not choſen you, (as moſt certainly he hath) he would not have ſo called you: he would never have juſtified you:<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> he would never have ſo glorified you with his gracious gifts, which I know, praiſed be his Name therefore: he would never have ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed your Faith with temptations, as he hath done and doth, if (I ſay) he had not choſen you.<note place="margin">Exerciſe of ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations a great token of election</note> I have choſen you (as doubtleſs dear heart, he hath done in Chriſt, for in you I have ſeen his earneſt, and before me, and to me you could not deny it, I know both where and when) if I ſay, he hath choſen you, then neither can you, nor ever ſhall you periſh. For if you fall, he putteth under his hand; you ſhall not lie ſtill: ſo careful is Chriſt your keeper over you. Never was Mother ſo mindful over her childe, as he is over you. And hath not he alwayes been ſo?</p>
            <p>Speak woman when did he finally forget you? And will he now, trow you, in your moſt need do otherwiſe, you calling upon
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:180526:59"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:180526:59"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:180526:60"/> him, and deſiring to pleaſe him? Ah my <hi>Joyce,</hi> think you God to be mutable?<note place="margin">Rom. 11.</note> Is he a changeling? Doth not he love to the end, them whom he loveth? Are not his gifts and calling ſuch, that he cannot repent him of them? for elſe were he no God. If you ſhould periſh, then wanted he power: for I am certain his will towards you is not to be doubted of. Hath not the Spirit, which is the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of truth,<note place="margin">Every lying ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit not to be hearkned unto Satan ſeeketh to bring tender conſciences to doubting: but Gods promiſe in Chriſt ſtandeth ſure for ever.</note> told you ſo? And will you now hearken, with <hi>Eve,</hi> to the lying ſpirit, which would have you not to deſpair (no, he goeth more craftily to work, howbeit to that end, if you ſhould give ear unto it, which God forbid) but to doubt and ſtand in a mammering, and ſo ſhould you never truly love God, but ſerve him of a ſervile fear, leſt he ſhould caſt you off for your unworthineſs and unthankfulneſs; as though your thankfulneſs or worthineſs were any cauſes with God, why he hath choſen you, or will final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly keep you.</p>
            <p>Ah mine own dear heart, Chriſt onely, Chriſt onely, and his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and truth.<note place="margin">All our election is in and for Chriſt only.</note> In him is the cauſe of your election. This Chriſt, this Mercy, this Truth of God remaineth for ever, is certain for ever, and ſo is your Election certain for ever, for ever, for ever; I ſay for ever. If an Angel of heaven ſhould tell you contrary, accurſed be he, accurſed be he. Your thankfulneſs and worthineſs are fruits and effects of your election, they are no cauſes. Theſe fruits and effects ſhall be ſo much more fruitful and effectual, by how much you waver not.</p>
            <p>Therefore (my dearly beloved) ariſe, and remember from whence you are fallen.<note place="margin">Pſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l. 120.</note> You have a Shepherd which neither ſlumbereth nor ſleepeth. No man nor devil can pull you out of his hands. Night and day he commandeth his Angels to keep you. Have you forgotten what I read to you out of the Pſalm, <hi>The Lord is my Shepherd,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 25.</note> 
               <hi>I can want nothing?</hi> Do you not know that God ſparred <hi>Noah</hi> in the Ark on the outſide, ſo that he could not get out? So hath he done to you, my good Siſter, ſo hath he done to you. Ten thouſand ſhall fall on your right hand,<note place="margin">Pſal 90.</note> and twenty thouſand on your left hand, yet no evil ſhall touch you. Say boldly there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,<note place="margin">Pſal. 125.</note> 
               <hi>Many a time from my youth up they have fought againſt me, but they have not prevailed:</hi> no, nor never ſhall prevail, for the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:180526:60"/> Lord is round about his people. And who are the people of God, but ſuch as hope in him? Happy are they that hope in the Lord: and you are one of thoſe, my dear heart, for I am aſſured you have hoped in the Lord: I have your words to ſhew moſt manifeſtly, and I know they were written unfeignedly. I need not to ſay, that even before God you have ſimply confeſſed to me, and that oftentimes, no leſs. And once if you had this hope,<note place="margin">Though feeling fail, yet let hope hold faſt.</note> as you doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs had it, though now you feel it not, yet ſhall you feel it again: for the anger of the Lord laſteth but a moment, but his mercy laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for ever. Tell me, my dear heart, who hath ſo weakned you? Surely not a perſwaſion which came from him that called you. For why ſhould you waver? Why ſhould you waver,<note place="margin">The eye of faith muſt look upon nothing elſe but onely Chriſt crucified.</note> and be ſo heavy hearted? Whom look you on? On your ſelf? on your worthineſs? on your thankfulneſs? on that which God requireth of you, as faith, hope, love, fear, joy, &amp;c. Then can you not but waver in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed: for what have you as God requireth? Believe you, hope you, love you, &amp;c. as much as you ſhould do? No, no, nor never can in this life. Ah my dearly beloved, have you ſo ſoon forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten that which ever ſhould be had in memory? namely, that when you would and ſhould be certain and quiet in Conſcience, then ſhould your Faith burſt throughout all things, not onely that you have in you, or elſe are in heaven, earth or hell, untill it come to Chriſt crucified, and the eternal ſweet mercies and goodneſs of God in Chriſt? Here, here is the reſting place, here is your Spouſes bed: creep into it, and in your arms of Faith embrace him: bewail your weakneſs, your unworthineſs, your diffidence, &amp;c. and you ſhall ſee he will turn to you. What ſaid I, You ſhall ſee? Nay, I ſhould have ſaid, You ſhall feel he will turn to you. You know that <hi>Moſes,</hi> when he went into the Mount to talk with God, he entred into a dark Cloud; and <hi>Elias</hi> had his face covered when God paſſed by. Both theſe dear friends of God, heard God, but they ſaw him not: but you would be preferred before them. See now, my dear heart, how covetous you are. Ah be thankful, be thankful. But God be praiſed that your covetouſneſs is <hi>Moſes</hi> covetouſneſs. Well, with him you ſhall be ſatisfied. But when? Forſooth when he ſhall appear. Here is not the time of ſeeing,<note place="margin">Pſal. 16.</note>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:180526:61"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:180526:61"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:180526:62"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:180526:62"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:180526:63"/> but as it were in a glaſs. <hi>Iſaac</hi> was deceived, becauſe he was not content with hearing onely.</p>
            <p>Therefore to make an end of theſe many words, wherewith I fear me I do but trouble you from better exerciſes: inaſmuch as you are indeed the childe of God, elect in Chriſt before the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of all times: inaſmuch as you are given to the cuſtody of Chriſt, as one of Gods moſt precious jewels: inaſmuch as Chriſt is faithful, and hitherto hath all power, ſo that you ſhall never periſh no, one hair of your head ſhall not be loſt. I beſeech you,<note place="margin">Learn here to put away doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, all tender hearts that ſeek after Chriſt.</note> I pray you, I deſire you I crave at you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hands with all my very heart, I ask of you with hand, pen, tongue, and minde, in Chriſt, through Chriſt, for Chriſt, for his Name, Blood, Mercies, Power, and Truths ſake (my moſt entirely beloved Siſter) that you admit no doubting of Gods finall Mercies towards you, howſoever you feel your ſelf: but complain to God, and crave of him as of your tender and dear Father, all things; and in that time which ſhall be moſt opportune, you ſhall finde and feel far above that your heart, or the heart of any creature can conceive, to your eternal joy. <hi>Amen, Amen, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The good Spirit of God alwayes keep us as his dear children: he comfort you, as I deſire to be comforted (my dearly beloved) for evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>This</hi> 8. <hi>of</hi> Auguſt,</date>
               </dateline> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>by him that in the Lord deſireth to you as well and as much felicity, as to his own heart.</hi> John Bradford.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:180526:63"/>
            <head>A worthy Anſwer of a conſtant Martyr called <hi>Guy de Brez,</hi> Anno Dom. <hi>1566.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>y de BreZ,</hi> a miniſter of the Goſpel, being committed Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner into the Caſtle of Tournay, was viſited by many Ladies and Gentlewomen, only out of a deſire to ſee him, in regard he was a man ſo highly eſteemed. Some at the firſt view ſcoffed; others railed on him; but others were moved to take pitty and compaſſion on him. Amongſt the reſt, the Counteſs of Ren, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with certain Gentlewomen, coming into the Priſon, and at her firſt entrance beholding the Iron chain to which was faſtned; Mr. <hi>Guy,</hi> ſaid ſhe, I wonder how you can either eat, drink, or ſleep in quiet, for wer I in your caſe, the very terrour thereof would goe nigh to kill me?</p>
            <p>O <hi>Madam,</hi> ſaid he, the good cauſe for which I ſuffer, and that inward peace of Conſcience with which God hath endued mee, makes me eat and drink with greater contentment then my enemies can which ſeek my life: yea ſo far off is it that my bonds or chain do any way terrifie me, or break off my ſleep, that on the contrary I glory and take delight therein, eſteeming them at a higher rate then chains and rings of Gold, or any other Jewels of price whatſoever; for they yield me much more profit. Yea when I hear the ratling of my chains, me thinks I hear as it were ſome ſweet inſtrument of muſick ſounding in mine ears: not that ſuch an effect comes meerly from my chains, but in regard I am bound therewith for maintaining the truth of the Goſpel.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>The ſame Martyr in a letter to his wife, acquaints her with Gods graci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>us dealing with him in all his aſſaults.</head>
            <p>SPeaking of his apprehenſion, he ſhews how carnal reaſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to play its part againſt the Providence of God; for ſaith he, theſe thoughts came thronging into my head; what meant we to go ſo many in company together as we did? had it not been for
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:180526:64"/> ſuch and ſuch we had never been diſcovered or taken. Under ſuch like cogitations I lay for a while, ſaith he, even in a manner over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed, till by the aſſiſtance of Gods holy Spirit my minde was raiſed up to meditate on Gods Providence. After which my heart began to feel wonderful reſt and contentment; ſaying thus in my ſelf, O my God, the day and hour of my birth was before ordained by thee, &amp; ever ſince thou haſt preſerved and kept me in great perils and dangers, and hitherto delivered me out of them all. And if now the hour be come wherein I muſt paſs out of this life into thy king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, thy holy will be done; I cannot eſcape out of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y hands; yea, though I could, yet Lord thou knoweſt I would not, ſeeing all my felicity depends upon conforming my Will unto thine.</p>
            <p>From theſe conſiderations I received no ſmall conſolation, and therefore, dear wife, rejoyce with mee, I pray you, and bleſs our good God for theſe his mercies towards me; for he do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h nothing but that which is equal and right. You have been privy to, and acquainted with all the travels, croſſes and perſecutions which have befallen me, yea, and have your ſelf been partaker with me therein, when you accompanied me in my voyages during the time of my exile: and now after all theſe you ſee, my welbeloved in the Lord, how he holdeth forth to mee his hand of Providence, to drive me home to himſelf into his bleſſed Kingdome. I now lead you the way, and when his will is you ſhall follow me thither. Our ſeparation ſhall not be for ever: it will not be long ere we be gathered under one head Jeſus Chriſt. This World is not the place of our reſt: no, Heaven is our home, this is but the place of our baniſhment. Let us therefore aſpire after our true Country, namely Heaven, and long to be received into the manſions of our heavenly Father, where we ſhall ſee our Head and Brother, our Husband and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, with the noble triumphant aſſemblies of the Patriarchs, Prophets, Apoſtles, and ſo many millions of Martyrs, to whom I hope ſhortly to be gathered, having finiſhed the courſe of that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration which I have received of the Lord Jeſus. Wherefore dear wife, be you comforted in the meditation of theſe things. Take into conſideration the honour the Lord doth you, in giving you a Husband who is not only called to be a Miniſter of Chriſts
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:180526:64"/> Goſpel, but alſo ſo highly advanced of God, as to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted worthy to partake of the Crown of Martyrdome. It is an honour which the Angels in Heaven are not capable of.<note place="margin">Angels not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome.</note> I now rejoyce in my ſufferings, my heart leapeth within me; in my Afflictions I finde nothing wanting unto mee; I am filled with the abundant riches of my God; yea ſo farre am I comforted therewith, that I have ſufficient ſtore not only for my ſelf, but to impart thereof alſo to as many as I have opportunity to ſpeak unto: which bounty and favour I beſeech my eternal Lord God to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue unto me his poor Priſoner: yea,<note place="margin">Gods goodneſs to his afflicted children is oft above and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation.</note> I am perſwaded that he will perform it unto the end; For by good expeience I feel, that be never forſakes them that truſt in him. I could never have imagin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that God would have been ſo gracious as he hath been to me his poor creature.</p>
            <p>I now taſte of the fidelity and bounty of Chriſt my Saviour: I am here taught to practiſe what I have preached unto others. Yea, let me not be aſhamed to confeſs, that when I heretofore preached I ſpake but as a Parrat, in regard of that which I have now better lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by proof and experience.<note place="margin">Priſons prove Gods School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes to the faithful.</note> I have profited more in the Schoolhouſe of this priſon, then ever I did in all my life before: for I have the Holy Ghoſt, who is my conſtant inſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cter and Schoolmaſter, teaching me how to handle my weapons in this fight of afflictions. Satan on the other ſide, who is the ſworn enemy of all Gods Elect, compaſſeth me about on every ſide as a roaring Lyon thinking to devour me. But he who hath ſaid, Fear not,<note place="margin">John 16.33.</note> I have overcome the World, puts as it were new courage into me; and then I ſee the Lord bruiſing Satan under my feet;<note place="margin">Rom. 16.20.</note> feeling the power of God perfected in my weakneſs:<note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.9.</note> and that the Lord cauſeth me one while to feel my infirmity and weakneſs,<note place="margin">It is profitable for the godly ſo c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es to feel their infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities.</note> that ſo I may take knowledge how I am but a poor earthen veſſel (even weakneſs it ſelf,) to hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble me, that God may have all the glory; and then by and by he fortifies and comforts me, (I may truly ſay) incredibly above all I could ask or think.</p>
            <p>For I would not change my condition with theirs who perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute me. I take my reſt, eat and drink with more hearts caſe then they. I am indeed lodged in the ſtrongeſt and vileſt Priſon they
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:180526:65"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:180526:65"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:180526:66"/> have, dark and obſcure, which for the darkneſs thereof is called <hi>Bruna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Brunain</hi> a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencians.</hi>
               </note> where I have no ayre to breathe at, but a little ſtinking hole, where they lay all their rubbiſh and where the drunkards commonly vent their Urine. I am laden with Irons both on my hands and feet,<note place="margin">By reaſon wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he complains he wrote with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uch difficulty, and therefore could not write as otherwiſe he would have done</note> which are a continual torment unto me; the irons eating through the fleſh, even to the bare bones. The Provoſt-Marſhal comes to view my Fetters twice or thrice <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> day, fearing leſt I ſhould make an eſcape: for preventing where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, he hath placed three Guards of Fourty men before the Priſon door, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And thus having given to his Wife his Advice, how to behave her ſelf during her Widowhood, and how to train up her Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, with his loving Salutations remembred to her ſelf, and other his ſpecial Friends, he cloſeth up his Letter.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
